<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true history of Cara Mustapha, late grand vizier being a most faithful account of his first rising, the several degrees of his fortune, his amours in the serraglio, his emplois, the true cause of his undertaking the siege of Vienna, together with the particulars of his death / written originally in French by a person of quality, and now translated in English by Francis Philon.</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25822</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09146996</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09146996</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1292:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true history of Cara Mustapha, late grand vizier being a most faithful account of his first rising, the several degrees of his fortune, his amours in the serraglio, his emplois, the true cause of his undertaking the siege of Vienna, together with the particulars of his death / written originally in French by a person of quality, and now translated in English by Francis Philon.</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
                  <author>Philon, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 139 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for L. Curtiss and Hen. Rhodes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE HISTORY OF CARA MUSTAPHA.</p>
            <p>Late GRAND VISIER.</p>
            <p>BEING <hi>A moſt faithful account of his firſt riſing, the ſeveral degrees of his Fortune, his Amours in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plois, the true cauſe of his undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Siege of</hi> Vienna, <hi>together with the particulars of his Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally in <hi>French</hi> by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of quality, and now tranſlated in <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>Francis Philon.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>L. Curtiſs</hi> on <hi>Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate hill,</hi> and <hi>Hen. Rodes</hi> next door to the <hi>Bear Tavern,</hi> near <hi>Bride-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:2"/>
            <p>The Strangling of the Grand Viſier.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>A. The Grand Viſier: B. The cheif officers of the Army aſsembled in council. C. The warrant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grand-Seignior for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grand Viſier; which he reads. D. an Aga holding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſilk rope to ſtrangle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grand Viſier. E. an Aga who preſenteth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grand Viſier a Cuſhion to Kneel upon, and pray. F. a velvet bag to put in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grand Viſiers head, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two Agas had order to ſever from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, after his being Strangled.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in Fleet ſtreet</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THis Book containeth the whole Life of <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> late Grand Viſier, who was Strangled laſt Year at <hi>Buda,</hi> by order of the Grand Seignior, his Enemies having turned into a crime, the neceſſity he had been brought unto, to raiſe the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> 'tis an Hiſtory, which hath deſerved a general approbation in its own Country, and 'tis not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but it will find the ſame accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in its Travels in <hi>England,</hi> being dreſſed up after the <hi>Engliſh</hi> faſhion. The moſt ſecret intrigues of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> are there traced with ſo much likely-hood, that it is impoſſible to forbear being convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb facs="tcp:42523:4"/>
that they have occaſioned all the misfortunes of this famous Miniſter.</p>
            <p>That Place which you ſee at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Book, may inſtruct you with the ſad manner, and fatal Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of his death; whilſt he was reading the Grand Seignior's Warrant for his Execution, one of the two <hi>Agas,</hi> who had been truſted with that cruel Commiſſion, ſet down before him a rich embroider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cuſhion to kneel upon, and make his laſt Prayer, and the other at the ſame time put a ſilk Rope about his Neck, and Strangled him; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out allowing him liberty to ſpeak a word, after he had ended his Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; There you ſee the <hi>Divan</hi> aſſembled, the Grand Viſier read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Order, the general amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the attendants, the joy of ſome, the trouble of the others, and all the circumſtances of that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:42523:4"/>
Spectacle, as they are explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the notes beneath. This Book recommends it ſelf ſo well by its own merit, that it would be needleſs for me to ſpeak any more in its commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; this only I will venture to ſay, that both they that ſeek meerly for paſtime, and pleaſure in the reading of a Book, cannot but take a great delight in ſeeing here the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle management of love tricks at the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Court; and thoſe that are for inſtruction, may be here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſatisfied, if they but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the wonderful revolutions, that appear in the whole ſtream of this great Man's fortune, from his very Cradle to his Death; nay, they that are truly pious will find here a fair opportunity to adore the Judgments of God, and confeſs that this Grand Viſier, who had contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Death of two eminent <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaws</hi> in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire,
<pb facs="tcp:42523:5"/>
was at laſt juſtly and deſervedly paid with his own coyn. In fine, they that are true Patriots, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to bear the glorious name of Engliſh Men, cannot but be very ſenſible of their happineſs, when they ſee in the ſeveral tranſactions of this Hiſtory, the moſt Tyrannical Government of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; they cannot, I ſay, but praiſe God, Love and Honour from the heart, our Moſt Gracious and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful King, when they conſider, how happy is the condition of Subjects, that live under a Monarch, who makes the Law the only Rule of his Government, in compariſon to that of thoſe, who groan under the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Yoke of a Prince, who follows no other rule, but his own will. I will put an end to this advertiſement, by giving a ſhort explanation of ſome obſcure terms, which I thought not fit to alter in the tranſlation of
<pb facs="tcp:42523:5"/>
this Book, to help thereby thoſe who have perhaps never heard of them in their life.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Serraglio</hi> means properly a Palace, but it is commonly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of that, wherein the Grand Seignior dwelleth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Port</hi> is the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Court.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> is the ſupream Miniſter of State, ſuch as were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the <hi>Mayors</hi> of the Palace in <hi>France;</hi> the <hi>Ximeneſſes</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and lately the <hi>Richelie us</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zarins</hi> beyond <hi>Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſhaws</hi> are like our Lords in <hi>England,</hi> who Commands the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and are made Governours in the ſeveral Provinces and Places of the Empire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beglierbey</hi> is a Viceroy of a whole Kingdom, who hath under him many <hi>Baſhaws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caplan Baſhaw</hi> is the High Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Turky,</hi> who not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb facs="tcp:42523:6"/>
the Fleet, but hath alſo Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over all Iſlands, and Seaport Towns, or Fortreſſes of the <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aga</hi> is a Colonel or Captain of a Troop, Regiment, or the whole Body of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> gradually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spahis</hi> is a Horſeman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cadi</hi> is the chief Juſtice of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or Town.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Divan</hi> is underſtood either of the aſſembly, or of the place of the Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Itchoglans,</hi> are young Men brod in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> almoſt after the manner of our Pages in <hi>Europe,</hi> they are ſent thither from all parts of the Empire, and choſen amongſt thoſe that the Governours ſend yearly to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as a tribute due to the Grand Seignior by the ſeveral Provinces.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Selam</hi> is a kind of Noſegay, or rather a little Basket full of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb facs="tcp:42523:6"/>
whoſe quality, colour, ſimetry and proportion, are as much expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of the paſſions of love amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> as our Billets or Love-letters in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but obſerve you at laſt, that the Hiſtory of <hi>Donna Emanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ela</hi> is not a fiction; 'tis an incident, the <hi>Gazett</hi> took notice of, at the time when that fair <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady was taken.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42523:7"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF CARA MUSTAPHA GRAND VISIER.</head>
            <p>OF all the Monarchies of the World, that of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> is without contradiction, the moſt deſpotick and abſolute: All the Subjects of that vaſt Empire, are Slaves to the <hi>Grand Seignior;</hi> Birth giveth no rank amongſt them; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do not inherit their Fathers E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; nay, the <hi>Baſhaws</hi> themſelves,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42523:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
know not their own Parents, the moſt part of them being ſtoll'n away in their moſt tender years, and brought into the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> wherein they learn all ſorts of Exerciſes. There they are bred in ſuch a great ſubmiſſion to the <hi>Sultan's</hi> orders, that they make to themſelves a principle of Religion, to yield up their heads without repining, when that Prince demands them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, being ſatisfied, they go ſtraightway to Heaven, if they be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py enough as to dye, either for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or by the Command of their Emperour. As the <hi>Sultans</hi> do ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily leave, all the care of the ſtate to the vigilancy of the Grand Viſier, that firſt Miniſter, hath a boundleſs and illimited Authority; he beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth favours as he liſts, and never wants fair pretences, to rid himſelf of thoſe who have diſpleas'd him. All the other Viſiers or <hi>Baſhaws</hi> give him an account of that, which concerns their Miniſtry, and the Emperour is never acquainted with other things, but ſuch as the Grand Viſier is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to have him know; even to that,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42523:8"/>
if the Prince comes to the <hi>Divan,</hi> that is the Council-board, his preſence ſerves for nothing elſe, but to give more credit to the motions of the Grand Viſier, which are always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of, without that any of the other Miniſters durſt contradict him. Nevertheleſs, that exceeding great power freeth him not from often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expoſed, to the danger of loſing his life, through the ſecret Cabals, which are contrived againſt him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> although he doeth his beſt endeavours to prevent them, by making ſure of the protection of the <hi>Sultaneſſes,</hi> and the friendſhip of the Eunuchs; and becauſe the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> are always ſenſible, either to love, or to ambition, and the Eunuchs do ſeek how to ſatisfie their inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble covetouſneſs, that gives occaſion to an infinite number of intrigues; ſo that, notwithſtanding the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cautions of the Grand Seignior, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he external rudeneſs of the Eunuchs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>here always paſſeth ſome ſecret ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry within the Palace, by ſuch like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itrigues <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> arrived to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42523:9"/>
the place of Grand Viſier; but, that we might give a more perfect and clear knowledge of it, we muſt come back and ſearch into the very Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the matter.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier <hi>Orcan,</hi> having diſpleaſed the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Queen <hi>Kioſem,</hi> was ſtrangled in the Reign of <hi>Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him.</hi> The Janiſſaries, who loved that Miniſter, revolted thereupon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to revenge his death. Their fury brought them to ſuch an extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that they cut off <hi>Ibrahim</hi>'s head, and ſet his Son on the Throne. That Son was but Six years old, who is this now Reigning Emperour, under the name of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Fourth. They did however conſent, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſhould be given to the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs Kioſem,</hi> Mother of him whom they had juſt now Sacrificed to their Vengeance. That Princeſs who had much Wiſdom, and was jealous of the pregnant wit of the <hi>Sultaneſs Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidè</hi> Mother to the Reigning Monarch, made a new Cabal for the undoing of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and ſetting up in his place <hi>Suleiman,</hi> his Brother, who was Son
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42523:9"/>
of another <hi>Sultaneſs.</hi> The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> having diſcovered that Intrigue, had intereſt enough among the <hi>Janiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> to put them upon a ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt. The Old <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> loſt her life in that ſedition, and the <hi>Sultaneſs Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidé,</hi> was proclamed Regent of the Empire. After all thoſe troubles, the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Monarchy enjoyed a long calm, through the great care of the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> and the peaceable temper of the Prime Viſier <hi>Boinou-Egri;</hi> but the Eunuch, who has the direction of the treaſure, having retrenched ſomething of the <hi>Spahis</hi> pay, which are the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe, they revolted, and made ſtrange diſorders. They could not be appeaſed, but by the Sacrifice of two of the chief Eunuchs of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> whom they ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led preſently; which ſo much incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> that they ever ſince that time, conceived an implacable hatred againſt the <hi>Spahis,</hi> and put all Engins at work for a revenge. Nay, the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> had a ſhare in their juſt reſentment, and promiſed them to take a convenient time for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42523:10"/>
of the Criminals. She ſpoke about it ſeveral times to the Grand Viſier; but that Miniſter, who had not courage and reſolution enough to undertake ſuch a dangerous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, found therein a great deal of difficulties: So the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> being preſſed by the Eunuchs, reſolved to cauſe the Grand Viſier to be depoſed, and deſigned for his Succeſſor the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Kioupruli,</hi> who had the repute of a fearleſs Soldier, and was account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Man of a vaſt capacity. She communicated her deſigns to the <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia,</hi> or Maſter of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and order'd him to wait upon <hi>Kioupruli</hi> from her, for to acquaint him with that great Fortune he was deſigned unto, thereby to engage him, to be for ever inviolably bound to her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts. The <hi>Sultan</hi> who Governed through his Mothers Councils, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of the reſolution ſhe had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. <hi>Boinou-Egri</hi> was turn'd out, and <hi>Kioupruli</hi> Proclamed Grand Viſier with a general applauſe. A little while after, he found a way how to diſunite the <hi>Spahis;</hi> they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42523:10"/>
and then ſeparately puniſhed for their revolt, by order of <hi>Kioupru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.</hi> That Miniſter having ſo anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the hopes of the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> got deep into the Grand Seigniors eſteem, and purchaſed the friendſhip of the Eunuchs, who have always e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince ſought the occaſions to ſhew him their ſenſibleneſs thereof; that which much contributed to the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the Grand Viſier <hi>Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha. Kioupruli</hi> who owned him to be his Kinſman, had put him in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> there to be brought up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a great number of young folks, that are called <hi>Itchoglans.</hi> The Eunuchs, the care of their breeding is committed unto, thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves happy to have frequent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of favouring <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who, of himſelf was a very comely and witty young Man, and did in all his Exerciſes, behave himſelf to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of the whole Court; ſo that, either by his own merit, or through the favour of the Maſter of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio,</hi> he got in leſs then ten years, into the Treaſure Chamber, which is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42523:11"/>
the poſt of diſtinction, and the firſt door of the Temple of Fortune; for the <hi>Itchoglans</hi> that ſerve there, do often approach the Grand Seigniors Perſon, and uſually arrive to the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt dignities of the State.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Beglierbey</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> being dead, his moſt precious goods were brought into the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s Treaſure, and becauſe there were found a great many moſt curious things, the Grand Seignior invited the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> his Mother to take a view of them; and although the like is almoſt never practiſed, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged her to come along with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Treaſure Chamber, attended by two of her <hi>Itchoglaneſſes,</hi> or Maids of Honour. The Officers who were not uſed to ſuch like viſits, were much ſurpriſed at. <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> diſtinguiſhed himſelf both by his good meen, and by a certain air of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, which none of the others could pretend unto; ſo that he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently obſerved by the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> who did, with great earneſtneſs look upon him. The Grand Seignior having perceived it, ſpoke of him moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorably,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42523:11"/>
and told her, he was Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew of <hi>Kioupruli.</hi> The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verjoyed to have ſuch a ſpecious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, to give him ſome token of that inclination ſhe begun to feel for him, asked the Grand Seignior a rich E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merald he had ſhewed her, and as ſhe had ſeen him beſtow many gifts upon the other Officers of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (which he is wont to do when he commands it to be opened) ſhe gave it to <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> who was ſo dazled at the ſight of Women, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perhaps never ſeen any till that day, that he durſt not accept of the Emerald, before the <hi>Sultan</hi> bad him to receive it. The <hi>Sultaneſs Valide</hi> retired, well ſatisfied with the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifick preſents her Son had made her, but with her mind filled with the ſweet <hi>Idea</hi> of the young <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who had appeared to her Eyes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding amiable: As ſoon as ſhe was alone, ſhe recalled to her mind, all the features of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> together with all ſhe had heard of his good parts; but when ſhe reflected on the impoſſibility of ever ſeeing again that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42523:12"/>
young <hi>Itchoglan,</hi> ſhe was ſorry that ſhe ſaw him; nay, ſhe earneſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to forget him. While ſhe was working upon her ſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer it, the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> or Maſter of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> who is a black Eunuch that commands all the others, put one day in his mind, to remit ſome dragm of his ſevere humour, and to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with the <hi>Itchoglaneſſes</hi> of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs Validé.</hi> Thoſe Maids who ſpend their life in a perpetual confinement, reſolved to fool him to ſome purpoſe; and accordingly, one of the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt feigned to love the <hi>Kehaia.</hi> The Eunuch obſerving, that the <hi>It<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choglaneſs</hi> uſed him with an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary kindneſs, could not forbear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, ſhe was indeed moved by his merit, and ſhew'd her a great ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs thereof. That young Perſon raviſhed with joy, for the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her trick, acquainted her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions withal, and continued to feign a vehement paſſion. Our Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, who had leſs love than vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, promiſed her, not reflecting upon his ſad condition; ſecretly to drop
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42523:12"/>
into her Chamber, when her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions were a ſleep. The <hi>Itchogla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> feigned to be moſt ſenſible at ſuch a proof of his affection, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him, ſhe would wait for his Eunuchſhip, with a great deal of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience; he failed not to come to the rendevous, and a minute after his coming, all the <hi>Itchoglaneſſes</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with Links, and ſcofft at the poor Wretch at an high rate. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuchs are revengeful People; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Kehaia</hi> took pett at this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, and reſolved to ſeek for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. In the mean while, the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs Validé</hi> did in vain reſiſt that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent paſſion, which drew impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly her heart towards <hi>Muſtapha.</hi> It grew ſo ſtrong with time, that ſhe more than once had a mind to get him ſecretly into her apartment; but the fear of endangering the life of ſo dear a lover, and thoſe almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conquerable difficulties, that ſhe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw would be found in making ſure of the Maſter of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> did plunge her into an unſpeakable trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mind. She heard in that very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42523:13"/>
time, by one of her <hi>Itchoglaneſſes,</hi> the merry trick they had played upon the <hi>Kehaia;</hi> and becauſe ſhe conſented and referred all things to her love, ſhe hoped, ſhe could draw ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage out of that adventure. She called privately the handſome <hi>Itcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaneſs,</hi> who had feigned to love the <hi>Kehaia;</hi> and after ſhe had repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto her, how much Eunuchs are inclined to vengeance, and that the <hi>Kehaia</hi> being Maſter of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> would not fail to undo her, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her her protection, and that ſhe would never forſake her, if ſhe would exactly follow her directions. That Maid being truly ſenſible of the Queens kindneſs, proffer'd her her own life, if ſuch a victim ſhould be neceſſary to her intereſts. Then the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> commanded her to feign ſtill to love the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> and to ſhew him both by deeds and words, ſhe was brought to deſpair, for the misfortune happened in their interview without her knowledge. The <hi>Itchoglaneſs</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged her commiſſion, with as much cunning as wit, but ſhe found the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42523:13"/>
Eunuch highly offended at the inſult he had, being expos'd unto whatever ſhe ſaid, he could not be perſwaded of her innocence: nevertheleſs, ſhe gave him ſo many ſigns of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream paſſion, that at laſt, ſhe made him believe it true. The poor <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia,</hi> was ſo much moved by the falſe ſhew of that fair ones tenderneſs and conſtancy, that then he felt more ſenſibly, than ever, the misfortune of his State; he was conſcious enough of his being utterly unable, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the forwardneſs of the young Maid, ſo it came in his mind to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in his room an <hi>Itchoglan</hi> of the treaſure houſe, hoping with that trick, to breed in his Miſtreſſes mind, an high apprehenſion of his Valour in Loves Wars, and that afterwards, he ſhould have the pleaſure of deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing her. That conceit ſo much tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and charmed his vanity, that he reſolved to ask young <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> if he would accept of a private conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with the handſomeſt of the two <hi>Itchoglaneſſes,</hi> which he ſaw wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé. Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:42523:14"/>
anſwered him out of hand, he would not be grieved to loſe his life after ſuch a happineſs. The Eunuch conceiving by that brisk anſwer, he could not chooſe a Man more proper for his deſign, told him, he ſhould e're long hear of him; and now, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had taken fair meaſures with his pretended Miſtriſs, he put <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> in diſguiſe, whom he had firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, how he muſt behave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to avoid the miſcarriage of an unlucky diſcovery. Night being come, he led him with unheards of precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions into the <hi>Itchoglaneſſes</hi> Chamber. The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all by that Maid, had taken her place, deſigning to catch the <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia,</hi> and threaten him with his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine, except he would make an atonement, and buy his pardon for his crime, by an entire ſubmiſſion to her commands, and the introducing young <hi>Muſtapha</hi> in her Chamber. As ſoon as he was come in, that <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> emboldened by her paſſion, and filled with the <hi>Idea</hi> of her Lover, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a dark Lanthorn, and did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42523:14"/>
begin to fright the falſe Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, with ſwinging reproaches, when ſhe knew again her dear <hi>Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha.</hi> There was never a ſurpriſe like hers; however it could not be but acceptable to her, ſince ſhe ſaw him whom ſhe had judged ſo worthy of her love, in lieu of a black and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eunuch, ſhe thought to meet with <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> on his ſide, was not ſo much pleaſed at the encounter as ſhe; having no experience in loves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues, he fell ſo much out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance at the ſight of the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> and was ſo frighted at her threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, that he durſt not lift up his eyes to look upon her, fancying the <hi>Kehaia</hi> would undo him, and that he was a going to be abandoned to the mercileſs fury of the dumbs of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> but our <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> did not leave him long in that fright. She plainly confeſſed him the violent paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhe had for him, and forgot no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might give him ſuch proofs thereof, as he could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, nay almoſt overwhelmed with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42523:15"/>
his <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> kindneſs, acquainted her with the deſign of the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> and how he put him upon cheating the <hi>Itchoglaneſs;</hi> ſhe heard that ſecret with a great deal of pleaſure, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe had promiſed him to take care of his fortune, ſhe ſent him back, ſtrictly forbidding him to tell the <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia,</hi> he had ſeen her.</p>
            <p>Now the Eunuch proud as can be, of an imaginary eſteem, he thought, he had got in his <hi>Itchoglaneſſes</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, did already affect to ſlight her, when the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> ſent for him; being come, and her waiting Ladies retired, ſhe told him, four dumbs were in ſearch of him, to ſtrangle him by the <hi>Sultan's</hi> order, becauſe he had, by Night, introduced a man into the <hi>Serraglio.</hi> The Wretch ſeized with fear, caſt himſelf at her Feet, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating her to be ſo merciful as to ſave his life. She engaged to ſue for his pardon, but on condition, he would confeſs his crime, and diſcover her all the circumſtances of that Affair, that might, ſaid ſhe, regard the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs</hi> Queen. The <hi>Kehaia</hi> made her
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42523:15"/>
unheards of Oaths to undeceive her, and after a downright ingenuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Itchoglaneſſes</hi> adventure, freely confeſſed, his vanity made him chooſe <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> to ſupply his place. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> well pleaſed at his honeſt dealing with her, made him conceive, ſhe knew well how to make a good turn to her friends, even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their application to her, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd him, he might retire without fear, becauſe ſhe had hindered the noiſe of his Crime, from coming to the Emperours knowledge. The <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia</hi> gave her a thouſand aſſurances of his gratitude, ſwore an inviolable attachment to her intereſts, and took his leave, a little while after, the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> who longed to ſee her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, called again the <hi>Kehaia</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, and declared to him, that ever ſince ſhe had ſeen <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> in the Treaſure-houſe, her mind was ſo filled with the charming <hi>Idea</hi> of his good meen, that it was impoſſible for her to think of any other thing, and that the moſt important and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervice he ever might do her,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42523:16"/>
was to introduce him at Night in her Chamber. The grateful Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch anſwered, he was exceeding glad he had opportunity to Sacrifice his life to her commands, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her to acquaint <hi>Muſtapha</hi> with ſo divine a fortune, that he might prepare himſelf to anſwer it, with ſuch forwardneſs as was due to ſo ſpecial a favour.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> having ſo cunningly engaged the chief Eunuch into the intereſt of her paſſion, got ſeveral times <hi>Muſtapha</hi> into her apartment; but ſcarce was their ſweet commerce well eſtabliſht, when the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier who minded his Nephews prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, took him out of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and put him amongſt the Troops, that he might give proof of his courage in the War. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> did reſent to the quick her Lovers departure, and wholly applyed her ſelf to ſeek how to have him back again, and at the ſame time to procure him an em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy, that ſhould engage him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide there. She had ſtill a great ſhare in the Government, ſo it was an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42523:16"/>
matter to her to find a favourable opportunity for that. The place of Maſter of the Horſe being vacant, ſhe moved the Grand Seignior to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it upon <hi>Cara Muſtapha;</hi> aſſuring him, the Prime Viſier would be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſenſible of it. The <hi>Sultan</hi> gave his conſent, and happy <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> is commanded to return ſpeedily to Court.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> having by theſe means, renewed her former correſpondence with her Lover, failed not to put an high value upon the ſervices ſhe had made him; and he failed not on his ſide to do his utmoſt, for being even with her, but in the midſt of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, he did not neglect his intereſt; he made ſo good uſe of thoſe ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advices ſhe gave him, for to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate himſelf in the Grand Signiors favour, that he honoured him with his ſpecial friendſhip, and gave him a little while after, a Commiſſion that ſhewed both a great truſt and eſteem. <hi>Aſſan Beglierbey</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> being revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the Grand Signior, had drawn in ſeveral other <hi>Baſhaws</hi> to his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42523:17"/>
party, and with impunity plundered all the frontiers of <hi>Anatoly.</hi> The Grand Viſier, had ſent a ſmall Body of Troops to fight that Rebel: but <hi>Aſſan</hi> was grown ſo powerful, that <hi>Kioupruli</hi> was forced to draw back his Army, and ſtay till he were able to ſend more conſiderable Forces thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Baſhaw</hi> had Marryed the Princeſs <hi>Baſh-lari,</hi> Siſter to the Grand Seignior, who had already been Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to three <hi>Baſhaws,</hi> tho then but between Sixteen or Seventeen Years Old. <hi>Aſſan,</hi> who was grown in years, had not, ſince his revolt, the ſame reſpects as afore, to that young Princeſs; her Birth Inſpiring her with a noble and Juſt pride, made her more ſenſible of the unkind uſage, ſhe received from him, ſhe could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uſe herſelf to it, and found a way how to ſend a Letter to the Grand Seignior, wherein ſhe complained to his Highneſs of her preſent miſery. The <hi>Sultan</hi> was moved at <hi>Baſh-lary's</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, and ſpoke of it one day to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> in ſuch Terms, as might
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42523:17"/>
plainly ſhew the greatneſs of his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. This was a ſufficient warrant to <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s Courage, he followed the Transport of his Zeal, and feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf extreamly Surpriſed, that there could be found upon Earth a man ſo baſe, and ſo unmannerly, as to want reſpect for a Princeſs of the <hi>Ottomans</hi> blood, he offered himſelf to feign a diſcontent from the Port, and go to <hi>Aſſan</hi>'s Army, to cut off his Head upon the firſt opportunity, if his Highneſs would but give him a Hatchérif. You muſt obſerve the <hi>Turks</hi> have ſo much Submiſſion for a Hatchérif (That is a warrant writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Grand Seignior's own hand) That, as ſoon as it is ſhew'd them, they give over their life, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to die, than to oppoſe ſuch an Order. The <hi>Sultan</hi> admiring the Zeal of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> accepted of his proffer, and made him depart ſecretly, authoriſed with a Hatchérif. <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s Journey was not long hidden to the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> and the Grand Viſier thought fit to acquaint her with the true motives thereof. She
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42523:18"/>
was ſo allarmed at the danger, her Gallant was like to be expoſed unto, that ſhe fell out with the <hi>Sultan</hi> her Son, and upbraided him with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach that he did, without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of good ſucceſs, Sacrifice the Nephew of a Miniſter, who ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with an Inviolable fidelity, giving him to underſtand at the ſame time, ſhe was confident, <hi>Kioupruli</hi> could never find comfort in ſuch a great loſs. The <hi>Sultan</hi> perſwaded by his Mothers reaſons, Commanded the Grand Viſier to ſend a Courier to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> to ſtop him in the way, and call him home again: but <hi>Kiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pruli,</hi> who had already a proſpect for the eſtabliſhing of his own Son's Fortune, ſcrupled not to hazard the life of his Nephew, for ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant ſervice to the State. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he told the Grand Seignior, <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> had already entred the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try occupied by the Rebels, and that his Couriers could not joyn him. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> was like to dye with grief, when ſhe heard of the unhappy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her cares, ſhe ſpent ſeveral
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42523:18"/>
days in a dreadful trouble and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of mind, and found no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but in the flattering hopes that fortune would perhaps help her Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers courage, he behaved himſelf with ſo much prudence, that he deceived the Rebel <hi>Aſſan,</hi> who reſted abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied, that indeed he was a Malecontent, and upon this account truſted him with a moſt conſiderable employ in his Army. Wiſe <hi>Muſtapha</hi> diſſembled for a while, but at laſt, ſitting one day at Table with <hi>Aſſan,</hi> and other <hi>Baſhaws</hi> of his Party, he drew out of his boſome the fatal hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherif, and having publickly read, and kiſſed it with a great deal of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſet upon the unfortunate <hi>Aſſan,</hi> and cut off his Head, and none of the <hi>Baſhaws</hi> offered to oppoſe him; which proves that Religion hath more influence, than policy in that blind obedience, the <hi>Turks</hi> pay to thoſe orders, that comes immediatly from the Grand Seignior. <hi>Aſſans</hi> death diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned ſo much all thoſe of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that afterwards, they endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make their peace at the Port.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:42523:19"/>Next to this Famous action, his firſt care was to look for the Princeſs <hi>Baſh-lari,</hi> who lived in <hi>Aſſan's Serra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> confounded with a great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of other ordinary Women, he waited upon her with all the reſpect due to a perſon of her rank, and begged her orders for the carrying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of all <hi>Aſſan</hi>'s goods, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to her by the Death of her Husband. <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> whom Old <hi>Aſſan</hi> did not uſe with ſo much civility, could hardly conceal her trouble, at ſo many Teſtimonies of reſpect from a man of ſo good meen. She ſtood a while ſpeechleſs, and gave time thereby to <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s Eyes, to view her exactly, and to ſatisfie himſelf, ſhe was one of the handſomeſt perſons upon Earth, he was himſelf ſo far ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of order, that he knew no more what to ſay, when by good luck, <hi>Aſſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſlaves, who caſt themſelves at hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> feet, begging his favour, Interrupted his ſo ſtedfaſt ſtaring upon her, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rebuked them ſeverely, and ſent them back to the Princeſs, declaring, ſhe was now the Sovereign Miſtriſs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42523:19"/>
their deſtiny. <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> could not but be very ſenſible of all <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s civilities, and throughly inflamed his heart with a moſt kind and obliging anſwer, ſhe made him. In the mean time, ſhe ſhewed a great deſire to return near the <hi>Sultan</hi> her Brother, and <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who was wholly poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the care to be officious, and complaiſant to her, gave all ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able orders for a ſpeedy departure. During the Journey, he did exactly wait upon her, and went ſo far, as to make her obſerve, the reſpect he owed to his Emperours Siſter, was but the leaſt motive of his ſo aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous attendance, and ſo exact a complaiſance for all her deſires. The Princeſs could not but perceive at laſt, that he loved her, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe was charm'd with his good meen and civilities, or dealt out of gratitude for that important ſervice, ſhe had juſt now received of him, in freeing her from <hi>Aſſan</hi>'s ſlavery, ſhe granted him the liberty, he with much earneſtneſs ſued for, to ſend her <hi>Selams</hi> in the Grand Seigniors
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42523:20"/>
               <hi>Serraglio. Selams</hi> are Noſegays made up of Flowers, which the <hi>Turks</hi> uſe inſtead of Love-letters.</p>
            <p>The News of <hi>Aſſan's</hi> overthrow, filled <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with Joy. The <hi>Sultan</hi> did applauſe himſelf, that he had alone concerted that enterpriſe with <hi>Cara Muſtapha.</hi> The Viſier was exceeding well pleaſed, to ſee the Empire freed by his Nephew from ſuch a dangerous Enemy; and for the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> ſhe was no leſs ſatisfied with the happy ſucceſs of her Gallants perilous undertaking, as if ſhe had her ſelf cut-off the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells Head. So <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> came back again, and was upon his return, welcomed and overwhelmed with Preſents. The old <hi>Kioupruli</hi> being ſick to death, made uſe of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable juncture to give the <hi>Sultan</hi> to underſtand, his Son alone had the ſecrets of the Empire; for he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways bred him with a proſpect to make of him a moſt able Miniſter of State. The Grand Seignior prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt with the Fathers former ſervices, and beſides that, being well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42523:20"/>
that the change of Miniſters is the greateſt plague and diſturbance, that may befal an Empire, thought fit to beſtow the Fathers place upon his Son, and accordingly Proclamed him Grand Viſier.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> ſtood as fair as any of the Court for Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet he was contented with his employ, and put upon this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration an high value before the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> who took it as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable proof of his love: But indeed, ſhe was no more but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of it. <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s heart was wholly devoted to fair <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> and if he anſwered the forward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> 'twas only to get thereby more means and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to court the Princeſs, 'twas not long e're he made uſe of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty ſhe had given him, he won with his Gifts, one of the Eunuchs that waited upon her, and ſent her by him a <hi>Selam</hi> made up with my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Flowers, which with a ſilent ſpeech ſet forth the violence of his paſſion for her, and how ſmarting
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42523:21"/>
and cruel was his grief, to ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf bereft of her ſight. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs kindly received his <hi>Selam,</hi> and to ſhew him how far ſhe was ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, ſhe returned him a Box fill'd with Musk ('tis obſervable, that among the <hi>Turks</hi> this Language is as much intelligible as Love-letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us) <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> was ſo raviſht with joy to ſee, through <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s anſwer, ſhe was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of his Love, that he fancied he might, in time Marry her, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the vaſt diſtance he ſaw betwixt his preſent ſtate, and ſuch a height of Fortune. This thought did ſo ſweetly flatter and tickle his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that he minded nothing elſe, but how to carry it on to an happy end; and becauſe he well knew, 'tis not lawful for any man to ask a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and that the Grand Seignior himſelf muſt chooſe him, he deems worthy of the honour of his alliance, he reſolved to court more aſſiduouſly the <hi>Sultan,</hi> that he might prefer him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42523:21"/>
before all them, that were in right to pretend to the poſſeſſion of <hi>Baſch-lari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hunting is the darling paſſion of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the fourth; <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> preſented him with a great number of choice Dogs, he had gathered from all parts of <hi>Europe;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Sultan</hi> grew thereby more fond of the ſport, and hunted ſince oftner than formerly: As many times as he Hunts, the Boars are commanded to encompaſs Six or Seven Miles about, a vaſt ſpace of Land, to the end that the game might not eſcape. Theſe frequent troubles being very tireſome to the People, and utterly defacing the Country, gave occaſion to great mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs and complaints, but however no body durſt tell the <hi>Sultan</hi> of it. The <hi>Mufty,</hi> which is the chief Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Law, ſpurred by his own zeal, and with the intreaties of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grave <hi>Baſhaws,</hi> reſolved at laſt to ventute on it, and fancied, he could, perhaps cure him of ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a paſſion, in urging to him this religious argument; <hi>that, when his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42523:22"/>
Predeceſſors were not in War, they uſed, to work with their own hands; that ſo illuſtrious an example might move their Subjects to give themſelves to uſeful things, no body daring ſtand idle, whilſt the Ruler of the World was buſie; that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Law it ſelf ordered the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to live upon their own labour, and not upon the ſweat of their Peoples Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brows, or the Money of Taxes. Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> repining at ſuch an unacceptable harangue, was ready many times to interrupt him, and ſhewed by his countenance and geſtures, that ſo free a diſcourſe did not pleaſe him. The <hi>Mufty,</hi> who already repented his having taken upon him that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Commiſſion, would a little ſweeten what he ſaid, and added, <hi>that if a handy-work ſhould vex the Prince, he might, to fulfill the Precept of the Law, make Arrows or any ſuch like ſmall pieces of work, that require little or no application;</hi> that as ſoon as the work is finiſht, he muſt but ſend it to ſome Wealthy <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> who would receive it with a great deal of reſpect, as made with the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42523:22"/>
Grand Seigniors own hand, and not fail to return his Highneſs ſuch a Magnifick preſent, as might abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly provide for the charges of his Table. The <hi>Sultan</hi> ſweetned with theſe laſt words, or perhaps, diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling his Anger, told the <hi>Mufty,</hi> that he took in good part his Fatherly remonſtrance, and aſſured him he would make uſe of it. <hi>Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> had been very attentive to that converſation, and well knowing that <hi>Mahomet,</hi> though very reſpectful to the Miniſters of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> yet doth not willingly ſuffer himſelf to be croſſed in his divertiſements, begged of him the honour of a private audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſpoke to him after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Cara Muſtapha, <hi>the humblest and devotedst of all thy Slaves, who uſeth his Ears, his Eyes, and his Tongue, but for the increaſing of the Glory of his Lord, not being able to endure that the</hi> Mufty <hi>ſhould abuſe the Sacred Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of his Character, preſume to make remonſtrances, and meddle with giving unſeaſonable advices to him that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42523:23"/>
gives the Law, wherever the Sun ſhines, not remembring, that all the goods of the Earth are his own, and that 'tis through a special favour, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth part thereof to his Slaves, doth with a deep ſenſe of humility ſhew thee, thou ſhouldeſt puniſh his raſhneſs, and yet not recede from his adviſe, leſt it might ſeem, the beloved of</hi> Alla <hi>and his Grand Prophet ſhould contemn his Law. Thou knoweſt, the</hi> Mufty <hi>is the moſt covetous and ſaving of all Men; If thou wilt then, mortifie him to the quick, thou muſt but go a hunting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſend him part of the Veniſon, thou haſt taken, with a word, that, to follow his ſacred admonition, thou haſt choſen the trade of a Hunter, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt him the fruit of thy labour; no doubt but he will liberally reward the Bearer, and return thee ſuch a preſent, as may largely provide for the Expences of thy diet. I am confident, if thou but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowest this my humble motion, he will no more in his life School his own Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> The Grand Seignior hearkned to <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s Speech with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable joy, gave him a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42523:23"/>
thanks, and vowed, he was more beholding to him for this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, than for the very head of <hi>Aſſan.</hi> Two days after he failed not to go a Hunting, and performed all he had reſolved upon with <hi>Muſtapha.</hi> The <hi>Mufti</hi> knew too late his fault in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his Sovereign's pleaſures, and was obliged to pay the honour he did him, with a very rich Preſent; and ever ſince that time, I warrant ye, he did never think of giving him ſuch Godly Admonitions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> was ſo entirely poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with the care of courting the Princeſs, that his ſo frequent and regular attendance upon the Grand Seignior, was rather the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of his love, than of his ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It fell out nevertheleſs, that this Monarch being extremely ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Services, began to think of ſetting up his Fortune, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Proclaimed him <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of the Sea. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> who look't upon this dignity, as a new ſtep towards the Princeſs, was overjoyed at the happy news thereof; aſſoon as his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42523:24"/>
preferment was publick at Court, all the Grandees of the Empire were very forward in complementing him thereupon, and ſent him rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, as is uſual in ſuch like occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but in the midſt of all theſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes, he thought of nothing but <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> and of preparing a rare <hi>Selam,</hi> that might with his ſilent Language, acquaint her with the true Sentiments of his aſpiring heart; after he had got into the <hi>Selam</hi> all thoſe Flowers he thought fitteſt to ſhew a ſtrong paſſion, and to let his Princeſs know, that he had accepted of the place of General of the Sea, but to have more opportunity to grow leſs unworthy of her, he truſted with it that Eunuch who had eſpouſed his intereſt, but this Block-head did ſo ill diſcharge his truſt, that being catcht by the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> he could never have eſcaped a moſt ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if he had not confeſſed, the <hi>Selam</hi> came from <hi>Cara Muſtapha.</hi> The <hi>Kehaia</hi> without any further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, doubted not but this Galan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try regarded the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:42523:24"/>
he warned the Eunuch never to take upon him ſuch Commiſſions, took the <hi>Selam</hi> out of his hands, and carried it himſelf in great haſt to the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> who ſometimes indeed was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with <hi>Selams</hi> by <hi>Cara Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha,</hi> but made up only with Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of a moſt reſpectful and ſenſible gratitude. She was ſo ſurpriſed, and at the ſame time ſo overjoyed that a Woman of her Age, was preſented with ſo tender a <hi>Selam,</hi> that not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now at hand what was neceſſary for a regular anſwer, ſhe bid the <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haia</hi> to bring him, next Night, into her apartment. In the mean time, <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> having heard of his <hi>Selam</hi>'s miſcarriage, attended all the day long upon the Grand Seignior, waiting for an opportunity to meet the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> who on his ſide was ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him. They met oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely together, the <hi>Kehaia</hi> ſhook <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s hand, and whiſpered him in the ear that he himſelf had deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his <hi>Selam,</hi> and was commanded to bring him that very Night, in ſuch a place where he ſhould be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42523:25"/>
thanked for it. The <hi>Sultan</hi>'s preſence did not permit him to explain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf farther, <hi>Muſtapha</hi> whoſe heart was fill'd with nothing but his royal Miſtriſs, was ſo agreeably ſurpriſed to hear, ſhe would ſee him, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other reflection, he wholly gave himſelf over to the tranſport of his Joy; and tickled in this critical minute, with the ſweeteſt hopes that may attend love, he lookt upon the Grand Seigniors condition as far leſs happy than his. The reſt of the day was long to him, he paſt it away in dreſſing up and undreſſing himſelf, never finding himſelf well enough, to appear before the Eyes of his <hi>Baſch-lari.</hi> This ſo long expected Night being come, the chief of the Eunuchs who uſed to guide him through dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways, for fear of meeting the Guard, got him ſafe into the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> Chamber. What pen might expreſs <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s amazement? he had flattered himſelf with the hope of ſeeing his Princeſs, now he finds himſelf unavoidably engaged with the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother! that <hi>Sultaneſs</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:42523:25"/>
beginning to preſs him hard, he could by no means maſter up his diſorder; ſhe perceived it, and begun to fall upon reproaches, when <hi>Muſtapha</hi> fearing leaſt ſhe ſhould dive into the true cauſe of his coldneſs, call'd back his wits about him, and told her that his new place forcing him ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to abſent from her, and put out to Sea, ſhe indeed wronged him with her wondering at his trouble. This witty and moſt ſeaſonable anſwer charmed the <hi>Sultaneſs;</hi> ſhe was ſo ſatisfied with <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> that far from ſearching any more into the Myſtery of his diſorder, it turn'd into a ſource of merit to him, ſo true it is, that a beloved one is eaſily credited and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted unto. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> diſmiſſed him, overloaded with all ſorts of careſſes, bid him to ground upon her protection in all things, and to be ſure ſhe would ſhortly ſee him call'd back at Court. So <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> very cleverly came off this time; he cleared afterwards with the <hi>Kehaia</hi> the matter of the <hi>Selam,</hi> but becauſe he knew him to be wholly
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42523:26"/>
devoted to the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> he took heed not to give him the leaſt hint of his love with <hi>Baſch-lari.</hi> Now, nothing being impoſſible to a man that loves indeed, he found a way how to ſend to the Princeſs another <hi>Selam,</hi> no leſs myſterious and tender than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, through the contrivance of a Jeweſs, that ſold Jewels in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and he had before parting this comfort to receive from her a Box full of Amber and Musk, which are the moſt open and expreſſive tokens of love, a Lady might give to her Lover.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as the new <hi>Caplan-Baſhaw</hi> had put to Sea, he bent himſelf whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the management of a glorious <hi>Campaign,</hi> hoping ſpeedily to return, and throw his Lawrels at the feet of his Princeſs, he gave chaſe to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chriſtian Corſairs, and met at laſt the Galleys of <hi>Maltha,</hi> which he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tached with much bravery: but a Prince of the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who commanded them, made ſo ſtout a defence, that after a long and cruel Combat, the Wind ſo parted both
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42523:26"/>
Fleets, that though they made their uttermoſt endeavours, they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver engage again one another. Two days after this Combat, the <hi>Turks</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Man of War, which they Fired upon, and took it after a very feeble reſiſtance. <hi>Cara Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> having called on board his Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captain, heard of him, that Ship was loaded with a great deal of precious goods, which the Viceroy of <hi>Naples,</hi> did ſend into <hi>Spain</hi> with his Daughter a beautifull Young Lady, who was a going to <hi>Madrit,</hi> in order to her being match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there with a Grandee. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> conceiving that amongſt ſo many rich goods, there might be found ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worthy of his Princeſs, ſtrictly forbad pillaging, and after he had got all the Soldiers out of the Ship, he came in and viewed her; he met firſt a number of Women bitterly weeping, who ſurrounded the fair <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, which he preſently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned through her ſingular beauty, and the State of her Garb. <hi>Cara Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha,</hi> whoſe courage, and Warlike
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42523:27"/>
temper were aſſwaged by love, tho the only Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> was the Goddeſs he thought worthy the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of his liberty, uſed his Slaves with kindneſs, and civilly anſwered the Petition of one of thoſe Maids, that ſpoke to him in <hi>Italian,</hi> and whom he obſerved to be very witty. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the riches of the Ship, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing pleaſed him ſo much, as a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour wrought with a great deal of art and Induſtry. It was encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with little <hi>Cupids,</hi> playing and ſaying to one another, <hi>felice chi e amato.</hi> Aſſoon as <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſaw it, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it for his Princeſs; the Captain of the Ship told him, it was a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece, which the ableſt workmen of <hi>Italy,</hi> had with emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion exerciſed their art on, and which was to be preſented to the Queen of <hi>Spain,</hi> from the Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> by the Famous <hi>Roxolane,</hi> the very ſame Maid, which ſpake juſt now with him, whom the Viceroy had with moſt advantageous proffers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was endowed with the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42523:27"/>
moſt pleaſant and harmonious Voice that might be heard upon Earth. This ſtirred up <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s curioſity; he diſcourſed again with <hi>Roxolane,</hi> who, notwithſtanding the great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhe was in, by ſuch a ſudden and cruel change of her condition, did nevertheleſs judiciouſly anſwer all his Queſtions: <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who aimed at his love in all things, conceiving, ſhe could do him a kindneſs near <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> reſolved to make her a preſent of that Slave, and the more to ingage her in his intereſt, he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her with much civility, and ſaw all her goods exactly reſtored to her. Nay, his kindneſs ſtayed not there, he was no great admirer of vocal muſick, however he deſired her to ſing, and after having highly praiſed her voice, he took this opportunity to preſent her with a Bracelet of Diamonds. <hi>Roxelane</hi> whoſe Birth was but mean, and who had bid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieu to her own Country, to purchaſe with her Voice thoſe advantages, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had refuſed to beſtow upon her, thought her ſelf fortunate in her ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:42523:28"/>
and left no argument untouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bring <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi> (ſuch was the fair <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies name) into a better temper, and to perſwade her, not to give her ſelf over to her ſorrow; but that fair one, who had not the ſame reaſons to bear up, did hearken to no counſels, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually weeping. Our <hi>Baſhaw</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Roxolane</hi> was mighty ſenſible of his civil and gentle carriage towards her, call'd her once in private, and after he had exaggerated the great account he made of a perſon of ſo rare and excellent qualifications, he told her, he would make of her the moſt happy Slave in the World, if ſhe would in good earneſt eſpouſe his intereſt, and engage to perform what he would preſcribe her. <hi>Roxolane</hi> who had but an ordinary ſhare of Beauty, and did never pretend to a very ſevere honeſty, was e'en apt to think ill of the <hi>Turks</hi> palate, and did already prepare a favourable anſwer to his Gallantry, when he imparted to her the ſecret of his paſſion, and his deſign to place her near <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:42523:28"/>
that ſhe might help his love, and keep the heart of the Princeſs beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his behalf; he made her ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticing a Picture of the inner part of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and of the happy life of them that wait upon the <hi>Sultaneſſes,</hi> that ſhe, hoping thereby to better her condition, promiſed him a blind obedience to his commands, and a careful and exact performance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> was exceeding well pleaſed at her readineſs, and now thought of ſending his Preſents to the <hi>Sultan</hi> and <hi>Sultaneſses,</hi> that he might have a colour to ſend to <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> the rich Looking-glaſs, without danger of diſcovering the Myſtery of his Love, he would fain have ſent <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi> to the Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, but being well acquainted with the fancy of the Prince, who was no way inclined to black beauties, and expecting an high ranſom from a Perſon of ſo eminent a quality, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd his mind.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the Preſents he ſent to <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> nothing was more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to her, than the mirrour;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42523:29"/>
but when a Chriſtian She-ſlave, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to her the <hi>Motto</hi> of the little <hi>Cupids, felice chie amato,</hi> ſhe did more attentively examined it, and found it more and more worthy of her eſteem, well conceiving, <hi>Cara Muſtapha</hi> would not have Preſented her with it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a deſign. The Voice of <hi>Roxelane</hi> was wondered at in the Palace, and both the <hi>Sultan</hi> and <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> would ſeveral times have the entertainment of her Singing; as for <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe was mighty pleaſed with it, yet ſhe made more of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, becauſe <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was always the ſubject matter of their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſhe did always commend to the Princeſs, either his good meen, his wit, his courage, or his unparalell'd paſſion for her: In all theſe diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhe did often mention the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, not being able to forbear praiſing her excellent parts, as many times as ſhe had occaſion to name her; and her indiſcreet zeal for <hi>Muſtapha</hi> went ſo far as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him ſeveral times for his civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and kindneſs towards this fair
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42523:29"/>
Slave. That unſeaſonable way of commendation wrought upon the Princeſſes mind quite contrary to her expectation; ſhe fancied it was not impoſſible but that Slave were loved by <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> ſince he had not ſent her to the Grand Seignior; in a word ſhe came to that height of ſuſpicion and jealouſie, that ſhe turned into as many crimes, all the particulars of the <hi>Baſhaws</hi> handſome uſage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Donna Emanuela.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> was indeed a great admirer of fine voices, but yet ſhe diſcovered new graces, unknown to any other but her, in <hi>Roxelane,</hi> when ſhe reflected upon her coming from <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and that ſhe could by her hear of the preſent condition, and circumſtances of her Lover. Therefore ſhe feigned to ſpend whole Nights without ſleeping, and upon this fair pretence, deſired <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> to give her <hi>Roxelane</hi> for a while, that the charm of her voice might eaſe her in her ſo long and troubleſome watches.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs durſt not refuſe her,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42523:30"/>
and paſſing by all the ſecret reaſons ſhe had to keep that Slave by her ſelf, ſhe muſt yield her to the intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother, for as long as ſhe would. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to work upon her with Preſents, then feigning her ſelf to be much concerned in her misfortunes, ſhe cunningly brought her upon the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, of the taking of the Man of War ſhe was Shipt in. <hi>Roxolane</hi> who ſerved the times, turn'd all to the advantage of the <hi>Turks,</hi> and inſerted in her diſcourſe ſo many paſſages glorious to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> that the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> was moved at them, and ſtuck not to tell her this <hi>Baſhaws</hi> intereſts were very dear to her remembrance, nay, that ſhe had juſt now procured him the place of <hi>Caimakan,</hi> which is the firſt dignity of the Empire, next to the Grand Viſier's. <hi>Roxolane</hi> raviſht with joy for theſe good news, went on in her Commendation of <hi>Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi>'s qualities, and well perceiving, the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> had an extraordinary kindneſs for him, even to ſhew a great deſire to ſee him poſſeſſed with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:42523:30"/>
his new dignity of <hi>Caimakan,</hi> which ſhould engage him to a conſtant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon the Grand Seignior, ſhe was deceived by ſo likely appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; and thinking, the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> inclination did not go farther than a vertuous eſteem for <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted her with the intrigue of his Love with <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> and earneſtly intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her to ſee that match made, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring her, ſhe could never do any better, or more acceptable ſervice to him, than this: So unexpected a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence ſmote the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> heart, like a Thunderbolt; ſhe bid her to tell again and again, what ſhe had indeed too well heard for her peace at the firſt time; and fearing, leſt the Slave might perceive the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable trouble ſhe was in, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her to remember <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s buſineſs, and quickly retired into her Cloſet, where ſhe gave her ſelf over to all ſuch tranſports, as a cruel jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie can breed in a ſlighted Woman. After a thouſand projects of revenge, ſhe found at laſt ſome comfort to think ſhe could, with her credit and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:42523:31"/>
intrigues, put a ſtop to a paſſion ſo ruinous both to her glory and love. She begun accordingly with ſeeking new pretences to keep <hi>Roxelane</hi> in her apartment, for fear ſhe might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> what had paſſed between them, and ſo quite ſpoil her deſigns.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, <hi>Muſtapha</hi> comes to the Court, where he finds himſelf far leſs ſenſible of the Grand Seigniors new preferment, than of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of being ſo near his adorable Princeſs. Upon his arrival he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the <hi>Sultan, Sultaneſſes,</hi> and chief Eunuchs with Magnifick Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents; and being conſcious of the ſo many obligations the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had heaped upon him, he thought it his next duty, to make application to the <hi>Kehaia</hi> for a ſecret entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with her; the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of his ingratitude, and yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding well pleaſed at his continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to court her, refuſed it at firſt, and ſent the Eunuch packing; but that motion of pride proved too weak, to reſiſt the plea of her own
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:42523:31"/>
heart in behalf of <hi>Muſtapha.</hi> She call'd back the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> e'en aſſoon as ſhe had bid him retire, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to bring with his uſual precautions, the <hi>Caimakan</hi> into her Chamber. Aſſoon as <hi>Muſtapha</hi> came in, he with an affected tranſport of joy, caſt himſelf at the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> feet; but ſhe, far from helping him up again, as ſhe uſed to do before, rebuked him ſeverely, and chooſe the moſt injurious reproaches to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid him with his perfidy. <hi>Vile Slave, ſaith ſhe, Chriſtian Brood, which I have from the very duſt of Mankind, lifted up to the ſecond dignity of this Grand Empire, doſt thou believe me ſo inſenſible of my glory, as to hearken to thy tales, while I am convinced, thou cheateſt me, and that with an unpreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented ingratitude, thou makeſt a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thy heart to a perſon famed, but by</hi> Aſſan<hi>'s ſlighting of her, and who is altogether unworthy to come into a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell with me, who am uſed to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorations of the Rulers of the World. Muſtapha</hi> overwhelmed with theſe ſo cruel reproaches of the <hi>Sultan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:42523:32"/>
and wondering at her being ſo far acquainted with his ſecret, durſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther anſwer, nor lift up his Eyes to look on her. <hi>Speak thou, perfidious Wretch, continued ſhe, ſpake, is it not true, thou loveſt</hi> Baſch-lari? <hi>I confeſs, anſwered then</hi> Muſtapha, <hi>that I have deſerved Death, ſince I have been ſo unfortunate as to incur your diſpleaſure, but canſt thou deny, replyed ſhe, that thou haſt ſent a Chriſtian Slave to the Princeſs, with a very ſtrict order never to let ſlip any occaſion to entertain her in thy favour? 'tis true, ſaid</hi> Muſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, <hi>I have ſent indeed a Slave to the Princeſs, and as I know that Chriſtians are very ill bred, and know not what respect is due to the</hi> Ottoman <hi>Blood, I will not diſown it, I took care to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct her; and becauſe ſhe doth not very well underſtand</hi> La Lingua Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, <hi>ſhe muſt needs have miſtaken my words.</hi> Though the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in her judgment, that he was guilty, yet ſhe did ſo much wiſh to have him cleared, that ſhe allowed of this ſlight reaſon, and heartily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave him, flattered with this thought,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42523:32"/>
that if he had felt ſome tender moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> he did truly repent it. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> took his leave after a World of Oaths, that he would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undergo a Thouſand Deaths, than to give her the leaſt occaſion of diſpleaſure; he was ſo much troubled at the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> anger, and over all, to ſee her ſo near acquainted with the Myſtery of his Love, that during a great many days he ſuffered all the torments a moſt diſquieted mind is ſubject unto, a Thouſand things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed him at once; on one ſide he feared the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> on the other, he loved <hi>Baſch lari;</hi> he would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> for fear of ruining his fortune; but he could not live, without hearing of his Princeſs; he was jealous of any thing he doubted, whether <hi>Roxelane</hi> had betrayed him or not; and in caſe he ſhould ſend a <hi>Selam</hi> to <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> he was afraid that the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> ſhould be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it. After he had long float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among ſo many vexatious thoughts, he reſolved at laſt upon undoing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, rather than to be any longer ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42523:33"/>
how his caſe ſtood in the Princeſs's mind. Another Eunuch, whom he won with much bribing, took upon himſelf to deliver into her own hands a <hi>Salam,</hi> by whoſe ſilent Language, he aſſured her, that he was inſenſible to any other pleaſure in the World, but to that of thinking he would love her for ever; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated her to believe that he had rejoyced at the new favour the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> was pleaſed of late to beſtow on him, but becauſe he grew thereby leſs unworthy of her alliance. In the mean time, <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> whoſe mind was ſtill poſſeſſed with the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the <hi>Caimakan</hi> Loved <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Emanuela,</hi> had ſince confirmed her ſelf into it, becauſe of the ſo long ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her lover, but more, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſince ſhe was told that having upon his return made ſeveral conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Preſents to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> he had ſtill kept by himſelf the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Such was her mind when the <hi>Selam</hi> came; ſhe hardly took time enough to view it, and returned pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently a ſmall Box, which <hi>Muſtapha</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:42523:33"/>
received with all joy imaginable, not doubting in the leaſt, but it was full of Musk and Amber. The great deſire, he had to know the true ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of his Princeſs, did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to put off one minute, the opening of the Box; but, oh ſtrange amazement! he found it fill'd up with Rue, which herb ſhews, in that Language of <hi>Selams,</hi> the uttermoſt indignation; he was near to dye with deſpair, at the ſight of ſo convincing a Witneſs of his misfortune; after he had long vexed his mind, and gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the true cauſe of his Miſtriſſes anger, he fancied that <hi>Roxelane</hi> had betrayed him; and upon this account conceived ſuch a general hatred for all Chriſtians, that without any other ground, he put a very ill uſage up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all thoſe, who were in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and cauſed <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi> to be clapt into a Dungeon, declaring her in plain <hi>Turk,</hi> her life ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to him for <hi>Roxelane</hi>'s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidy. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, who did not apprehend the meaning of theſe words, and dayly expected to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42523:34"/>
by her Parents, was ſo fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Caimakan</hi>'s threatnings, that ſhe laid ſeveral days under the horrours of preſent Death, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any comfort or hope of ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering her liberty.</p>
            <p>Now, the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> who was not yet undeceived about the pretended infidelity of her Lover, made her buſineſs to ſpeak upon any occaſion of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady's perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, even to that degree of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly malice, that ſhe ſaid in the preſence of the Grand Seignior, that if all that, <hi>Roxelane</hi> publiſhed of that Chriſtian Womans charms were true, there was no ſuch beauty in all the <hi>Serraglio.</hi> This word ſlipt out of her mouth as at unawares, ſtirred up the curioſity of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> for that he had not preſented him with that handſome Slave, and bid him to ſend for her forthwith. She was brought, but ſo changed by the ſorrow ſhe felt for the loſs of her liberty, and the bad uſage of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> that the Grand Seignior found not her beauty an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42523:34"/>
to the Picture, <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> made him of it; however ſhe remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Palace, and did neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs give great jealouſie to the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> who had been allarmed at the report of her perfections, and at the Grand Seignior's earneſtneſs to ſee her. <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> whoſe jealous Eyes found out a Hundred faults in her Face and Features, delighted much in vexing that poor innocent Maid, and asked her, one day, if ſhe was not very ſorry to part from the <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makan. Donna Emanuela</hi> modeſtly anſwered, that ever ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her captivity, ſhe knew no interruption in her misfortunes; that however, ſhe found her condition much bettered in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> ſince ſhe was no more expoſed to the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the moſt cruel Man in the World, ſhe was moved at theſe words, and with great eagerneſs deſcanted upon the hard uſage, ſhe had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Muſtapha.</hi> The Princeſs, though ſhe much pitied the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Maids miſery, did nevertheleſs feel a ſecret tickling joy at thoſe complaints
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42523:35"/>
ſhe made againſt her Lover; and though one cannot but be moved at the hearing of a Friend's misfortune, yet 'tis very true, that in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, all the cruelties of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> to his Slave, were put to account of merit by <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> who knew, at laſt, her errour, and much repented her having ſent to him a <hi>Selam</hi> made up with Rue. After ſhe was fully convinced of the injuſtice of her ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion, ſhe felt a ſecret ſhame for it, and upbraided her ſelf with her jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, as a weakneſs unworthy of an <hi>Ottoman</hi> Princeſs. In the mean while, the <hi>Caimakan</hi> vexed to the higheſt degree at the laſt tokens of her anger, was ſtill minding how to juſtifie himſelf; 'twas hard to do it: The Pallace was inacceſſible to him, he durſt not truſt the Eunuchs, and ſaw a Thouſand almoſt invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſtacles, that oppoſed his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> however all thoſe difficulties diſheartned him not. It came in his mind to make appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> her Mother. She lived in the old <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42523:35"/>
becauſe the Perſons that are ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are not kept under ſo ſtrict a confinement, as in the other, it was eaſie to him to ſend Preſents to that <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> who ſeeing her ſelf out of favour, was overjoyed, that one of the moſt powerful Officers of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ſhould ſeek for her Friendſhip. She made on her ſide all ſuitable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to anſwer the eſteem he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her, and meet him half the way; ſo that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſeeing her well diſpoſed, acquainted her with his Love for the Princeſs her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and aſſur'd her, if he ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver become her Son in Law, ſhe might expect from him an entire, and perfect obedience to her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> did joyfully approve of his wooing, and proffer'd him her intereſt at Court to bring him to happineſs. The <hi>Caimakan</hi> thanked her with much reſpect, but let her underſtand, 'twas more to the purpoſe to make ſure of the heart of the Princeſs, than of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. The <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> upon the firſt opportunity failed not to ſpeak a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42523:36"/>
good word to her Daughter in favour of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and ſhewed her the great advantages, that muſt needs attend her Marrying ſo puiſſant a Miniſter. That long ſilence, the <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makan</hi> had been forced unto, did a little perplex the Princeſs's mind; therefore, ſhe was not ſorry, that her Mother would manage her inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and ſhe anſwered her, with a bluſh, ſhe would willingly Marry <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> if the Grand Seignior com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it. That converſation was not hidden to the <hi>Caimakan; Baſch-lari</hi>'s Mother gave him a faithful ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof; and conceiving through the modeſty of her anſwer, that ſhe was appeaſed, he ſent her a <hi>Selam,</hi> wherein he got ſuch Flowers as might beſt aſſure her of the unſhaken fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his love, and of the pleaſure, he felt for his being reconciled with her. The Princeſs was not inſenſible of his great zeal; at firſt, ſhe would have return'd him a Box full of all ſorts of perfumes, but upon better thoughts, and leaſt ſo kind a <hi>Selam</hi> might ſhew too much the ſentiments
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:42523:36"/>
of her heart, ſhe was contented to ſend him a Box, wherein he found a ſmall piece of white linnen, which is a token of peace, he received it with much ſatisfaction, nay he would have it inchaſed into a rich Watch, which ever ſince he wore always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, kiſſing it a Thouſand times in a day.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> who was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting new pretences to keep <hi>Roxolane</hi> by her, that ſhe might not ſpeak to the Princeſs in behalf of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha,</hi> begun at laſt to perceive, he was grown leſs forward in his duties, and attendance upon her than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. This remiſsneſs permitted her not to doubt any longer, but he was bound Slave to the Princeſs, her jealouſie diſcover'd to her, ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances, that in the firſt tranſport of her anger, ſhe thought of utterly undoing that ungrateful <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> but having not vertue enough to countenance ſo violent a reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe fancied, that if <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> were once Marryed, <hi>Muſtapha</hi> having no more hope to arrive to the poſſeſſion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42523:37"/>
of his Miſtriſs, might eaſily forget her: As ſhe had ſtill much credit with the Grand Seignior her Son, 'twas not long e're ſhe moved to him a Match for the Princeſs, and urged ſo many reaſons for it, that he gave his conſent, caſting his eyes upon the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> to honour him with his alliance; he ſent him word there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by a Hatcherif, and bid him forthwith to take his Journey to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi> The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> raviſht with Joy, for a ſucceſs ſo advantageous to her paſſion, did no more trouble her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for any good office, <hi>Roxelane</hi> might do to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and ſent her back to the Princeſs, who found no ſmall comfort in complaining with her, of that cruel Match ſhe was threatned with; as for the unfortunate <hi>Caima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan,</hi> nothing may be compared with his grief, when he heard of a decree that left no hopes to his Love. The <hi>Sultan</hi>'s orders being all irrevocable, he gave himſelf over to deſpair, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing at all that might help him: The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> was grown odious to his remembrance, becauſe he knew
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42523:37"/>
well, ſhe had alone adviſed that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. The Grand Seignior ſeem'd unjuſt to his Judgment; nay, his own fortune was burdenſome to him, ſince he could no more, either ſhare it with, or ſacrifice it to the only perſon upon Earth, for whoſe ſake he loved to live. In this ſo general conſternation of his mind, he thought, he might eaſe himſelf, if he could but ſee his Princeſs pay ſome Tears, or ſome ſighs to their diſappointment. The fancy of ſo ſlight a comfort flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered him to ſuch a degree, that, <hi>maugré</hi> all dangers, that attended the Execution of this bold enterpriſe, he reſolved to ſpeak with her, chooſing rather to periſh than to be deprived of that Comfort. So having taken a reſolution ſo ſuitable to his love and deſpair, he begged a private audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother, who commanded the <hi>Kehaia</hi> to introduce him by Night, diſguiſed in a Maids garb, as he was uſed to do; he got then into the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and leaving aſide the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi>'s apartment, he went ſtraightway to <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:42523:38"/>
his garb deceived the Eunuchs that waited in her Chamber; they thought this <hi>Itchoglaneſs</hi> came from the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs</hi> Mother, and gave her full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to approach the Princeſs, who was little leſs caſt down than her Lover, for whether her heart ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaded for him, or ſhe feared to fall again into the hands of an Old Man, after the ſad experiment ſhe had made of <hi>Aſſan</hi>'s contempt, the very thought of her Match brought her to deſpair. She was much aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at the ſight of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and though her ſurpriſe and trouble hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her to apprehend throughly, the dreadful danger he had run him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into, ſhe nevertheleſs, blamed the boldneſs of his attempt; but, what have I to ſpare, when I loſe you, fair Princeſs, ſaith he; ſince I muſt needs dye with grief, if I ſee you in any other Man's arms than mine, I had rather to dye by the hands of the Mutes, than to be forced to behold ſo diſmal a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle. <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s heart melted into Tears at theſe words, and left to her Eyes the care to give him a Thouſand
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:42523:38"/>
Witneſſes of her gratitude, for ſuch a proof of his Love: but while they are ſo tenderly ingaged, the <hi>Sulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> Mother who waited for her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, wondring at his not coming, ſent for the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> who aſſur'd her, that he had long ſince let in the <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makan,</hi> and attended him pretty near her own Chamber. Then all her jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie awaked, ſhe doubted not but he was with the Princeſs, and fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a fury to ſee her ſelf ſlighted by a Man, who notwithſtanding thoſe ſo many favours ſhe had heaped upon him, uſed her as a Cloak to cover his Love for another, that without any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Examination, ſhe came to the <hi>Kaden</hi> or Governeſs of the Maids, and bid her preſently to adviſe the Grand Seignior, that a Man had dropped into the Womens apartment, and at the ſame time ſent word to the Mutes of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> that they ſhould be ready for the puniſhment of that raſh mortal, aſſoon as the Grand Seigniors Orders were come, the Eunuchs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſeek after that Wretch, who was eaſily found out juſt as he was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:42523:39"/>
going to rejoyn the <hi>Kehaia.</hi> The <hi>Sultan</hi> highly incenſed at a boldneſs almoſt without preſident, would not have him Strangled by the Mutes; this Puniſhment not ſeeming to his Juſtice, cruel enough for ſo enormous a crime, he commanded, he ſhould be the next day publickly impaled in the great yard of the Palace. The <hi>Kehaia</hi> himſelf was arreſted, becauſe he is accountable for all that comes into the Womens <hi>Serraglio.</hi> Now the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> hearing of the cruel decree of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> ſpent the whole Night in a great perplexity of mind. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe applauſed her ſelf, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered her paſſion with the hope of being ſoon revenged of her treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Gallant, but a minute after ſhe repented to have cauſed ſuch a noiſe, and feared leaſt the <hi>Caimakan</hi> would diſcover her ſecret commerce with him; pity ſucceeded theſe wiſe refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. That puniſhment, he was threatned with, ſeemed to her too cruel for a crime, which had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principle but Love; and beſides that, minding that <hi>Baſch lari</hi>'s Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:42523:39"/>
was reſolved upon, and that her departure would have infallibly broken the two Lovers meaſures, ſhe curſed her own tranſport, and was in an extream impatience to ſee the break of day, that ſhe might go and beg the criminal's pardon. She thought moreover, if ſhe diſcovered to the <hi>Sultan,</hi> that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> had been ſo bold as to enter into <hi>Baſch-lari's</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, it would be a hard caſe to hinder his death, and though ſhe found an unvaluable pleaſure in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing her rival, yet ſhe chooſe to bereave her ſelf of it, and renounce ſo tickling and ſo ſweet a revenge, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to exaſperate her Sons ſpirit with ſo odious a circumſtance. At break of day, ſhe run into the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> apartment. Dear Lyon, ſaith ſhe, it is the <hi>Caimakan,</hi> who hath been found diſguiſed in a Maids garb; no doubt, the violent paſſion, he had for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, put him out of his wits; I am very ſorry for it, becauſe he was a faithful Servant to thy Highneſs, he deſerves indeed to dye; but, thy ſervice being prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:42523:40"/>
before all, look thou whether it be not leſs inconvenient, to pardon him, than to deprive thy ſelf of a Miniſter ſo zealous of thy glory. The <hi>Sultan</hi> ſurpriſed at the name of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> call'd to mind, in that critical minute, the great and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſervices he had received from him, and finding much likely-hood in all that his Mother ſaid, he told her he was ſorry, that he had been arreſted, becauſe he did not at all concern himſelf for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Slave, nay that he had repented to have taken her away from him.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, he granted his pardon, but was not ſo indulgent to the <hi>Kehaia,</hi> whom he commanded abſolutely to be ſtrangled; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſued for his life; that, though with much ado, ſhe at laſt obtained he ſhould not dye; but he muſt loſe his place, and be turned out of the Palace. So <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, when he expected nothing but Death, and as great Monarchs know well how to ſeaſon their favours,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:42523:40"/>
The <hi>Sultan</hi> being perſwaded, he was in Love with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, ſent her back again to him two days after, and <hi>Muſtapha</hi> had ever ſince that time, all reſpect imaginable for <hi>Donna Emanuela,</hi> becauſe he lookt upon her as the Grand Seignior's Slave. In the mean while, the very terrours of Death had not been able to diminiſh his Love; he was on the contrary ſo bewitched with <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s charms, ſince his private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with her, that he grew more ſenſible than ever of that fatal Marriage, which was to rob him of his Princeſs, but eſpecially, when he heard, the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo</hi> her fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Husband was upon his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and would ſhortly arrive at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> This news allarmed him ſo much, and his hatred for that rival increaſed to ſuch a degree, that he wholly bent his wit, to find a way how to undo him, and becauſe he knew well, that the <hi>Baſhaws</hi> who have Governments afar off the Court, do endeavour to grow rich by all ſorts of wicked ways, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:42523:41"/>
durſt not complain of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, but after they are called home, he ſent one of his confidents to <hi>Aleppo,</hi> who did cunningly publiſh every where, that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> ſhould never come back again. This falſe report wrought in the Peoples mind, as far as <hi>Muſtapha</hi> could wiſh, an infinite number of complaints were made againſt the <hi>Baſhaw;</hi> and the <hi>Cadi</hi> of <hi>Aleppo,</hi> who had a ſecret Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the <hi>Caimakan,</hi> to examine carefully all that might ſerve a turn againſt him, he ſent, in a few days, to the Grand Viſier, an ample me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of all his cruelties and miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors, he made the report there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the <hi>Divan,</hi> in the preſence of the Grand Seignior, who was ſo highly offended and incenſed thereby, that not expecting ſo much as the Grand Viſiers Vote, he ſent preſently a Chiaoux with a hatcherif to fetch his Head. This unfortunate <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> having no reaſon to fear ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Grand Seignior, who had lately deſigned him his Brother in Law, bid his Steward to bring
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:42523:41"/>
the Chiaoux into a magnifick apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he had prepared for the Princeſs with great cares and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite expences. After he had given him ſufficient time to view all the riches of the place, that he might give a favourable account thereof to the Grand Seignior, he came to him to know what was his errand. The <hi>Chiaoux</hi> ſerved him with the fatal Hatcherif, and without any other complement threw a ſilk rope on his Neck, and Strangled him preſently. The Princeſs, who hated that Old <hi>Baſhaw,</hi> had the good fortune to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in his vaſt Eſtate, though ſhe never ſaw him in her life; and <hi>Muſtapha</hi> being ſo happily rid of one whoſe life was ſo great an hindrance to his love, flattered himſelf now that nothing would oppoſe his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and contrived with the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother of <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> that upon the next <hi>Bayram,</hi> at which time the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſſes</hi> of the Old <hi>Serraglio</hi> wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Grand Seignior, ſhe ſhould recommend her Daughters intereſt to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:42523:42"/>
his Highneſs, and move to him the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Match.</p>
            <p>Although the ſecret commerce of <hi>Muſtapha</hi> with the <hi>Sultaneſs Valide</hi> was ended, with the favour of the chief Eunuch, yet he ſtill managed her protection, and ſometimes ſent <hi>Selams</hi> to her, wherein he affected to ſhew himſelf very ſorrowful, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo long bereft of the happineſs of her preſence. Theſe Witneſſes of a remnant of love did very little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the <hi>Sultaneſs.</hi> She doubted not but <hi>Muſtapha</hi> had much contributed to the Death of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo;</hi> however, becauſe Women do not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly part with any of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, ſhe accepted of his <hi>Selams,</hi> and feigned to believe what they meant, but ſhe nevertheleſs, minded of Marrying <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> and removing her from the Port. The Grand Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er being dead in this juncture, all the Subjects of that vaſt Empire ſtood in great expectation of him that ſhould be raiſed to that height of honours. The <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> and prime Eunuchs made their intereſts, every
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:42523:42"/>
one in favour of their particular friends; but the <hi>Sultan,</hi> who had a great inclination to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred him before all the other can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates, and Proclaimed him his Grand Viſier, whereupon he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the complements of the whole Court, his very Enemies being the forwardeſt of all in ſending Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Preſents to him. The <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> whoſe intereſt it is to keep a good correſpondency with that firſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſent ſecretly their emiſſaries to complement him in their behalf, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them reſpectively, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to let him underſtand, they had had a great influence in the Grand Seignior's choice. <hi>Cara Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi> being ſo arrived to the higheſt dignity a Subject of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire may aſpire unto, did no more doubt but the <hi>Sultan</hi> would honour him with his alliance, and give him the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> in Marriage, and if ſometimes his love made him apprehenſive, and fearful of ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, he preſently relyed upon the Grandeur of his fortune, which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:42523:43"/>
lifted him above all other Viſiers and <hi>Baſhaws,</hi> that might pretend to the poſſeſſion of his Miſtriſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bayram</hi> being come, the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneſs Krali</hi> a very ambitious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who hoped to get again in the Government of the State, if ever the Grand Viſier ſhould Marry her Daughter, waited upon the Grand Seignior, and ſo cunningly wrought upon him, that he approved of the Match, and promiſed her, he would ſhortly ſee it accompliſht. She fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to acquaint the Grand Viſier with the good ſucceſs of her viſit, who was ſo tranſported with joy at theſe happy news that he ſet all his Slaves at liberty, the fair <hi>Spaniſh</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy alone did not enjoy that favour, becauſe having once entred the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>'s <hi>Serraglio,</hi> the Viſier could not free her without his ſpecial Warrant; but that Prime Miniſter uſed her with ſo much civility and kindneſs, that ſuch a captivity might have been pleaſant to any other, but this charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maid, who had ſecret reaſons to bewail ſtill the miſery of her State.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:42523:43"/>
although the Grand Viſier had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed liberty to all his Slaves, yet there was found amongſt them a young man of very good meen, who refuſed it. The Viſier referring his refuſal to the great Zeal he had for his ſervice; proffered him ſeveral ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous conditions, if he would turn <hi>Turk.</hi> The Slave anſwered him, he was ſo well ſatisfied with his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that he would not change it for that of any <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of the Port. So proud an anſwer ſurpriſed the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, who cauſed him to be ſecretly obſerved, he that was charged with it, acquainted him a little while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that this young Slave ſpent whole Nights in weeping under the Windows of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady. The Viſier conceiving he was in love with her, commanded him to be put in Fetters, and having ſent for <hi>Donna Emanuela,</hi> told her, in a jeſting way, that a Chriſtian Slave did ſo paſſionately Love her, that he ſpent whole Nights under her Window, lying upon the ground; but that he would ſoon ſee her rid of that ſilly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42523:44"/>
Gallant, and cure him of his folly, with a daily doze of Five Hundred Baſtinadoes. She grew pale at theſe laſt words, and a deluge of Tears breaking out of her Eyes, ſtirr'd up the curioſity of the Grand Viſier, who earneſtly intreated her to tell him whether ſhe knew that Slave. <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi> ſeeing herſelf betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by her Tears, reſolved to diſcover her ſecret, and being afraid, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier might perhaps, put a bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon her conduct, ſhe ſpoke to him in theſe terms.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:42523:44"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF DONNA EMANUELA</head>
            <p>THat unhappy Slave you ſpeak of, my Lord, is called <hi>Don Gaspard de Toledo,</hi> he is of one of the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Families in <hi>Spain, Donna Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria de Mendoza</hi> his Mother, was bred together with mine in the Queens Palace, both under the quality of Maids of Honour; and though beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth always breed envy amongſt Perſons of the ſame rank in Royal Houſes, yet there was ſuch a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of humours and principles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, that they never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed any thing one from another,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42523:45"/>
and loved themſelves withas much ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity as tenderneſs. They were both Married the ſame year, and their love proved no leſs fervent and true after their Marriage, than while they were Maids. About the Years end <hi>Donna Maria</hi> was brought to Bed of the unfortunate <hi>Don Gaſpard;</hi> as for my Mother ſhe found her ſelf big with Child but three years after, and you ſee my Lord the product of her breeding. <hi>Donna Maria</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad that my Mother had brought into the World a Daughter, and e'en aſſoon as I was born, ſhe demanded me in Marriage for her Son; our Planets approved of our Mothers deſign, and bred between us ſuch a ſympathy, that we did prefer the pleaſure of being together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other divertiſements ſuitable to our Age; but our happineſs ended almoſt aſſoon as we begun to know it. <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> was near twelve, and I eight years old, when my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſent Ambaſſador to <hi>Rome,</hi> and took along with him all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; our Parents were very buſie,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42523:45"/>
how to give us ſome comfort in this hard ſeparation, and found no better way to ſweeten our grief, than to conclude our Marriage, which was done with all uſual formalities, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both ſigned it by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>My Fathers Ambaſſy laſted Six Years, and becauſe he had been at vaſt expences in <hi>Rome,</hi> the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Naples</hi> was beſtowed upon him, as a recompence for his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; ſo that my Mother foreſeeing, we could not return ſo ſoon in <hi>Spain,</hi> wrote to that of <hi>Don Gaspard,</hi> and deſired her to ſend him into <hi>Italy.</hi> They gave him an equipage anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his birth, and he departed. But <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> who then begun to be ſenſible of Martial glory, hearing of the Wars in the low Countries, took his Journey towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> and thought no more of <hi>Naples.</hi> My Mother who had been acquainted with his departure from <hi>Spain,</hi> was in a great trouble for him, and I muſt confeſs to you, my Lord, that I had a great ſhare in her ſorrow,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42523:46"/>
a while after we had intelligence from <hi>Madrit,</hi> that he was in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> My Father was ſo offended at his coldneſs, or rather, ſlighting of me, that he would have broken all the bounds of our Engagement, had not my Mother ſweetned his anger, and taken him from that reſolution, though with no ſmall pain. Peace having ſucceeded the War between the two Crowns, which balance the Affairs of <hi>Europe,</hi> and <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> having no more occaſion to get glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, felt ſome impatience to ſee me again, but he was willing to ſatisfie his curioſity without being known, he came to <hi>Milan,</hi> and having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated his deſign to the Prince of <hi>Ligne,</hi> who was then Governour of that Dukedom, he earneſtly intreated him to give him leave to go under the name of his Son, and to write a recommendatory Letter to my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that upon account of their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient friendſhip, he might hope a kind reception from him. The Prince, who was not ignorant of my being long ſince Married with <hi>Don Gaspard,</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:42523:46"/>
conceiving, he would uſe that Letter only to play upon me ſome gallant trick, that ſhould, at moſt, laſt one day or two, granted it to him in what manner he was pleaſed to have it. <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> arrived at <hi>Naples,</hi> where he paſſed eaſily for the Prince of <hi>Ligne</hi>'s Son, for he was ſo chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince his Child-hood, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy knew him again. My Father gave him an apartment in his Palace, and forgot nothing that might Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the great eſteem he had both for the Father and the Son. The firſt time, I ſaw him at <hi>Naples,</hi> I wiſhed, my Lover might be as well made as he, he entertained me with ſo much wit, and I diſcovered in his Perſon ſo many excellent qualities, that I had a ſecret ſhame within my ſelf for that natural inclination I felt for him, fancying that I ought to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem none in the World but <hi>Don Gaspard;</hi> ſo that I reſolved to ſhun the Company of a Cavalier, whoſe ſight might prove ſo ruinous to my vertue. In the mean time, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being extremely ſcandalized to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42523:47"/>
hear no more of <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> although the peace was made, was ſo ſatisfied with the young Prince of <hi>Ligne,</hi> that he ſaid ſeveral times to my Mother, he would willingly have him to his Son in Law, my Mother gave him a Thouſand reaſons to the contrary, and though ſhe did agree with him about the merit of the young Prince, yet ſhe could not reſolve to turn out the Son of <hi>Donna Mendoza</hi> her Friend. I had much to ſuffer in this juncture. My Father on one ſide would have me no more think of <hi>Don Gaſpard;</hi> on the other, my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repreſented to me as ſo many crimes, the leaſt thoughts of any other but him who was deſigned to be my Husband. My perplexity was ſuch as cannot be well imagined. I could not keep me from a great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem for the Prince of <hi>Ligne,</hi> but however my heart ſtood firm for <hi>Don Gaſpard.</hi> I will not trouble you, My Lord, with the ſeveral ways he uſed to corrupt my vertue, which held out againſt all his attacks; nay, I did ſo happily hide from him the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42523:47"/>
ſecret motions of my heart, that he could never obſerve in my conduct any thing that might give him the leaſt hope. A little while after, my Father received a Letter from the Governour of <hi>Milan,</hi> wherein he begged his pardon for the little cheat he had put upon him, in writing a recommendatory Letter to him for <hi>Don Gaſpard de Toledo,</hi> under the Name of his Son, and wiſhed him much Joy for having choſen a Son in Law endowed with ſo many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent parts. As he was already prepoſſeſt with a great eſteem for the Prince, he was overjoyed to find in him the true <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> he ſent immediatly for him, and all the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants being retired, he embraced him with all the tenderneſs of a true Father, approved of his witty Plot and permitted him to carry it on ſtill. <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> who fell at firſt in no ſmall confuſion, to ſee himſelf diſcovered, confeſſed to my Father, he had thought fit to know me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Marriage, for fear of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into that inconveniency which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:42523:48"/>
is ſo common amongſt <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who ſlight their Wives, becauſe hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never ſeen them before their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, they uſe themſelves to a poſſeſſion which was never mixed nor ſeaſoned with any allarm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently they never feel for them but very lukewarm and languiſhing paſſions; he added ſo many things to my advantage, that I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe them without a bluſh. My Father left him, being extremely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dified to ſee ſo much wiſdom in ſo tender a Youth. That very ſame day, he would have him ſit at Table with my Mother and me, which is lookt upon in our Country, as a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extraordinary favour, my Mother repined at it, and did her utmoſt to hinder it; but ſeeing my Father would abſolutely have it ſo, ſhe ceaſed to oppoſe it. After meat ſhe retired in her Chamber, and I was obliged to follow her. She told me, with tears, that ſhe could not apprehend the meaning of her Husband, but intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me never to forget that I was bound to <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> and feign a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42523:48"/>
Diſtemper rather than ſit again at Table with the Prince of <hi>Ligne.</hi> In the mean time, my Father not being able to ſee my Mother any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in a bad humour, let her know that the falſe Prince of <hi>Ligne</hi> was the true <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> in Witneſs whereof he ſhewed her the Letter of the Governour of <hi>Milan.</hi> There was never a Joy like hers. She embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her Husband an Hundred times, and recalling in her mind <hi>Don Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi>'s features, ſhe found that, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he reſembled <hi>Donna Maria de Mendoza,</hi> and ſhe could not imagine how ſhe might have ſtaid ſo long in ſo groſs an errour. She was in a great impatience to ſee <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> and imbrace him, but my Father who had bound himſelf to ſecret, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated her to be ſilent, nay to conceal ſtill from me the buſineſs for a while, as I was ignorant of all theſe particulars, I lived in a great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of mind. I pleaded indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to my Mothers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but yet I inſinuated to my Father, that I was well enough to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42523:49"/>
go and ſit at Table with him, he was angry with me, for that out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance to her, I failed once to be there, but on a ſudden, I ſaw a ſtrange alteration in my Mother's carriage, ſhe did no more oppoſe it, on the contrary, ſhe bid me fit at Table every day juſt by the Prince, and dreſſed me with her own Jewels to ſet off my Beauty; I perceived at the ſame time, that ſhe had an extraordinary kindneſs for him upon all occaſions; nay, ſhe affected to withdraw in her Cloſet after meal, and commanded me to ſtay by my Father, who uſually plaid at Cheſs with an old Chaplain of his, ſo that the falſe Prince was in full liberty to court me; which indeed he perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo much paſſion, and in ſo tender and inticing a manner, that I was e'en ready to ſurrender, when my Mother did well perceive my weakneſs, and being afraid like a prudent Woman, that I would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps too favourably anſwer his Fires, and that <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> would not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the Princes's progreſs upon
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:42523:49"/>
my heart, diſcovered me the intrigue of his diſguiſe, and recommended me over all, not to give him the leaſt ſuſpicion that I were acquainted with it. I reſolved at firſt to be revenged of this trick, and to puniſh him ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who was the contriver thereof; but it was impoſſible for me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble long, and I found ſo much pleaſure in thinking that I could, without failing to my former engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> ſatisfie the ſecret Inclination I had to the Prince, that I had not vertue enough to ſhew him the leaſt indignation; nay, far from frowning upon him, I ſought his company, and admired all that he ſaid, and kept with him as long as decency could allow, and when I was obliged to retire, it was always with a ſecret impatience to ſee him again; he had for me the ſame ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I had for him, but with this notable difference, that he enjoyed the pleaſure to expreſs them to me an Hundred times a day, whereas I lived in a continual reſerve, being forced to conceal mine from him,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:42523:50"/>
but at laſt his paſſion grew ſo violent that he came to my Father, deſired him to accompany him to my apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to tell me his true name, and bring quickly our Marriage to an happy concluſion. I was ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, when my Father preſented him to me, and I was ſo little attentive to his complement, that I have quite forgot it; but this I remember well, that <hi>Naples</hi> was preparing to honour our Wedding with Magnifick Feaſts, and all manner of publick rejoycings, juſt at the time when Letters came from <hi>Spain,</hi> by which we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the Death of <hi>Don Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard</hi>'s Father. This unſeaſonable news broke all our meaſures. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> ſhould ride Poſt to <hi>Madrit,</hi> and that, for his Mother's comfort, we ſhould be Married in <hi>Spain,</hi> whither I was to go by Sea three Months after. I will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, My Lord, with the ſad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our grief, when we left one another; but it is certain that I had a foreſight of thoſe misfortunes that have befallen us ſince, and that I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42523:50"/>
ſwooned away within my Mothers Arms, when he took his leave of me. Aſſoon as he was arrived in <hi>Spain,</hi> he wrote to my Father, and deſired him to ſend me thither before the three Months we had agreed upon were expired. My Father who had a great deſire to ſee me Married with that young Lord; whoſe merit and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue were well known to him, thought fit to grant him his requeſt; I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barked, and after a long and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome Navigation, our Sea-men told us, they had diſcovered the Coaſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> this news made me forget all the toils of ſo painful a Journey, and I did already flatter my ſelf with the hopes of ſeeing ſhortly my Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who expected me at <hi>Barcelona,</hi> when you made your ſelf Maſter of our Ship. <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi>'s heart was broke at the tidings of my ſad ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, his courage or rather his Love, did not permit him to ſtay for any ſuccour from my Father. He provided himſelf with a conſiderable Summ of Money, and took Ship to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome Religious Men,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:42523:51"/>
who depart every year from <hi>Spain,</hi> for the Redemption of Chriſtian Slaves in the Dominions of the Grand Seignior; having Landed at <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> he was told, that I could no more be Redeemed, becauſe I was ſhut up in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and what care ſoever he took to hear of me, it was impoſſible for him to do it. All his Friends adviſed him to return home, but he would not follow their Counſels, he ſtayed in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> though bereft of all hopes of ever ſeeing me again, he heard neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of ſome <hi>Jews,</hi> that I had been ſent back in your <hi>Serraglio;</hi> he prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them an ample reward, if they could but get him a place in your Houſhould. As nothing ſeems hard to thoſe Mercenary Souls, when they have a proſpect to ſatisfie their inſatiable avarice, they gave him great hopes; but however, after they had vainly tryed all ſorts of ways to compaſs their deſign, they told him 'twas altogether impoſſible to do it, becauſe, there was no Preſident that a <hi>Muſſulman</hi> had ever kept Chriſtians
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42523:51"/>
in his ſervice, except they were his Slaves. Theſe difficulties diſheartned him not, and he did very willingly conſent that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould ſell him to your <hi>Kehaia;</hi> after which he found a way at laſt how to diſcover him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to me, and notwithſtanding the great alteration of his fortune, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently knew him again. Now ſee, my Lord, continued <hi>Donna Emanue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> if he deſerves to be ſo ſeverely dealt with as you had deſigned.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier was moved at this Speech, and after he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his <hi>Kehaia</hi> to ſee <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> put out of Fetters, he aſſured the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lady, that her condition was not ſo unfortunate as ſhe fancied, ſince the Grand Seignior whoſe Slave ſhe was could permit her to Marry her Lover, and beſtow upon them both ſuch an Eſtate, as might equal if not ſurpaſs that which they had left behind them in their own Country; that they ſhould but cauſe themſelves to be inſtructed with the Law of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> to enable him thereby to ſpeak in their behalf to the <hi>Sultan,</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:42523:52"/>
and procure them all manners of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits from his Highneſs; which elſe he could not do, becauſe his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did forbid him to concur any way to the ſettlement of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; he would or could not ſtay for her anſwer, but ſent immediatly to both of them; his Doctors to teach them the Precepts of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coran,</hi> being very confident, that loving one another to ſuch an high degree of tenderneſs, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver refuſe thoſe ſo advantageous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions he proffered to them; but theſe couple of Heroick Souls ſtood firm and unſhaken in their Religion, and after they had given one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Thouſand aſſurances, that their mutual love ſhould indure as long as their life, they reſolved in preſence of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Divines, rather to dye than to renounce Chriſtianity. The Grand Viſier being acquainted with their reſolution ſpoke again to <hi>Donna Emanuela,</hi> and let her know that ſhe muſt bid an eternal farewell to <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> if ſhe would be ſo obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent upon her Religion; nay, that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:42523:52"/>
he was a going to embark him in a Ship, that was ready to ſail for <hi>Spain,</hi> but all theſe threatnings did not ſhake her conſtancy. She anſwered ſtill with the ſame courage, and her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue carried it over her Love. The Grand Viſier applyed himſelf next to <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> urged to him all ſorts of reaſons and arguments drawn out of the intereſt of his Love and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but all in vain, ſo that ſeeing it was not lawful for him, according to the Principles of his Religion, to help them in theſe circumſtances, he forced the <hi>Jews,</hi> who had ſold <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> to pay his ranſom, and ſent him back in his own Country.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Grand Viſier waited with an unſpeakable impatience, for the Grand Seignior's Orders upon his Marriage with the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari;</hi> that Monarch who did never take a final reſolution upon any thing, but more eſpecially upon ſuch matters as regarded the Princes, or Princeſſes of his Family, without firſt conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> his Mother, imparted to her his deſign to match
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42523:53"/>
the Grand Viſier with his Siſter, and related to her all thoſe reaſons, the <hi>Sultaneſs Krali</hi> had urged to him, to move him thereunto. The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> needed the ſuccour of all his wit to put by this dreadful Blow. She feigned at firſt to approve of the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s project, and added yet other reaſons to confirm her Son in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: but (oh what is not a cunning and jealous Woman capable to do) after a ſilence of ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhe ſaid, that when the Prince hath once truſted a Miniſter with the whole conduct of his Empire, he cannot be too cautious, or do too much to engage him in his intereſt by all poſſible means; that, for her, for from diſliking a deſign ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the good of the State, ſhe thought 'twas not enough to Match his Siſter with the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, but moved further that, to bind him with a nearer alliance, he ought to give him his Daughter, though then but Five Years old. She upheld her motion with ſo many other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, that ſhe perſwaded the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42523:53"/>
Grand Seignior of the reaſonableneſs thereof, and he promiſed her to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. This <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> whoſe aim was only to break the meaſures of our Lovers, was not contented with the reſolution of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> to make of the Grand Viſier his Son in Law, her jealouſie did yet require a more cruel revenge. She ſhewed a great concern for the eſtabliſhment of the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> and intreated the <hi>Sultan</hi> to prevent all the complaints of the <hi>Sultaneſs Krali</hi> her Mother, by Matching her with <hi>Baſhaw Aſaſp,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom at the ſame time he might beſtow the Government of <hi>Buda,</hi> which is one of the moſt important and conſiderable poſt of the whole Empire. The Grand Seignior having approved of all his Mother's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, thanked her for her great Zeal to his intereſt; the next day he ſent for <hi>Cara Muſtapha,</hi> to whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his reſolution to honour him with his alliance, by giving him in Marriage his only Daughter, which was the richeſt and deareſt treaſure he had in the World, and the infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libleſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42523:54"/>
Witneſs, he might have of his being fully ſatisfied with his ſervices. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> ſtood ſo amazed, and ſo overwhelmed with anguiſh at this cruel diſcourſe, that the <hi>Sultan</hi> ſhould have certainly perceived the great trouble, which was ſpread all over his Face and Perſon, had not he, to hide his commotion, caſt himſelf at the Feet of his Maſter, which he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced a long while, without utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Word. The <hi>Sultan</hi> who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed this reſpectful ſilence to an exceſs of ioy for ſo pleaſant a news, told him at the ſame time of <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s Match with <hi>Baſhaw Aſaſp,</hi> whom upon account thereof he made Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Buda:</hi> The unfortunate Viſier reſented this addition of grief in a manner, that can be better ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined than expreſſed. The <hi>Sultan</hi> ſeeing him ſtill proſtrated at his Feet, and that he would not riſe up, thought to the purpoſe to ſpare him the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of an anſwer, upon ſo nice an Affair, and retired ſtill perſwading himſelf, that <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s ſilence could
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42523:54"/>
have no other cauſe but the exceſs of his Joy.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as he was alone, he gave himſelf over to deſpair, ſeeing no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the whole World more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy than his, he revolved in his mind, that he had arrived to the higheſt dignities of the Empire, far leſs by his ambition, than by his Love, which had made him vigilant and active in hope of pleaſing his Princeſs; that after he had ventured his life to inform her of his paſſion, that ſame love had prompted him with means how to undo the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo</hi> her deſigned Husband; that he had rejoyced at his preferment to the place of Grand Viſier, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he grew thereby leſs unworthy of his Princeſs; that he had ingaged the <hi>Sultaneſs Krali</hi> to ſpeak in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; that the Grand Seignior had liked the motion of his Match, and that after all that he muſt ſpend his life in a continual Slavery with a Child of Five Years, and ſee his Princeſs in another's Arm, or to ſay better, never ſee her any more, ſince
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:42523:55"/>
ſhe muſt go to <hi>Buda</hi> with her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; theſe cruel reflections afflicted him ſo much, that he ſhould have forgot to ſend the uſual preſents to the Grand Seignior's Daughter, had not his friends, hearing of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour this Monarch had beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, earneſtly intreated him to anſwer it, and to preſent the Young Princeſs with Slaves, Toilets, Gowns, and Jewels, according as it is practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſuch like occaſions. The Grand Viſier paſſed many days in private, during which he granted au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to no Body, and found no better comfort than to let <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> know his deſpair, and aſſure her, that in ſpight of all the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niors violence and injuſtice, he was reſolved to venture a Thouſand lives, for to convince her, he would love her to his laſt breath; but <hi>Baſhaw Aſaſp</hi> having uſed the Precaution to draw in, with rich preſents, the <hi>Sultaneſs Krali</hi> to his party, ſhe ſpoke to her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his Favour, and cunningly let her underſtand, that the Grand Viſier,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42523:55"/>
being Maſter of the Empire, it would have been eaſie for him to Marry her, if ſacrificing his love to his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, he had not preferred the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Son in Law, of the Grand Seignior before that of Brother. The Princeſs who found a great likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in her Mothers reaſons, was ſenſibly moved at that contempt, and reſolved to forget the Grand Viſier; but all the efforts ſhe made to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer it, were fruitleſs. She endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſtifle that ſecret inclination, ſhe felt for him; but it had got ſo deep and ſo ſtrong a root within her heart, that this rebellious heart did always revolt againſt her reaſon; and all that ſhe had been told of her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ingratitude, was not ſufficient to blot out his ſweet <hi>Idea</hi> of her mind; however, though ſhe had an extreme repugnancy for a March with <hi>Baſhaw Aſaſp,</hi> ſhe muſt follow the ſtream of her deſtiny, and her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made her at laſt reſolve to obey the irrevocable Orders of the Grand Seignior. The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> whoſe aim was only to remove, aſſoon as
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42523:56"/>
ſhe could, ſo dangerous a rival, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the <hi>Sultan</hi> to make her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part upon the very ſame day of the Ceremony of her Marriage, which was performed with ſuch rigour, that ſhe had not ſo much liberty allowed to her, as to wait upon her Mother in the old <hi>Serraglio,</hi> to bid her the laſt adieu. The Grand Viſier got ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs his <hi>Selam</hi> preſented to the Princeſs, that ſame fatal day; ſhe received it without knowing almoſt what ſhe was a doing, being toſſed with an infinite number of confuſed and oppoſite motions; yet, <hi>maugré</hi> her anger, and all thoſe bounds ſhe had juſt now entred into, ſhe found ſome comfort in receiving a <hi>Selam</hi> from her Lover, though ſhe conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he could not alledge any good reaſon, to excuſe his perfidy; but when ſhe knew through the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and quality of the Flowers the <hi>Selam</hi> was compounded with, that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> was brought to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, and aſſured her of an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting love, that knowledge ſerved but to increaſe her grief, and to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42523:56"/>
make her more ſenſible of ſo cruel a ſeparation. <hi>Roxelane</hi> who with her diſcourſes had always nouriſhed and cultivated her love for the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, in hopes of obtaining her liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty after their Marriage, was no leſs caſt down than her Lady. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of ſentiments, or perhaps, a ſecret pleaſure the Princeſs felt in talking of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> with a Perſon that was in his intereſt, made her complain to that Slave, for to try her mind, of the perfidy of the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who after having made a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of her to his ambition, was yet ſo cruel as to increaſe her anguiſh with vain endeavours to perſwade her by moſt paſſionate <hi>Selams,</hi> that he did loſe her to his great grief, and would never ceaſe to love her; <hi>Roxelane</hi> forgot nothing that might juſtifie the Grand Viſier, and the Princeſs was ſo ready to allow of all that could do it, that ſhe eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, the <hi>Sultan</hi> had forced him to Marry his Daughter; but when ſhe reflected upon her Mothers reaſons, and that the Grand Viſier, being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42523:57"/>
Maſter in the Empire could have taken other meaſures to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent her miſery, ſhe preſently conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he had never had for her but an ordinary paſſion, ſince he had not oppoſed her Match with <hi>Baſhaw A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaſp,</hi> as he did with the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo;</hi> as theſe reflections did inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs her glory, ſhe was ſo overpower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, that ſhe took a final reſolution never to hear of him, and accuſtomed herſelf by degrees to the careſſes of her Husband, who uſed her with all imaginable reſpect and kindneſs.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier being inconſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon the Princeſſes departure, gave over the Government, and ſpent ſome Months in ſuch a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing condition, that they deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired of his Life. Nevertheleſs with time, and the remedies of the ableſt Phyſitians of the Empire, he reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his former health, and took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the care of the State. Aſſoon as he begun to recover, the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> who was no more afraid of a rival, made ſeveral ſteps towards
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42523:57"/>
him, for the renewing of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, but the Viſier, who could not forget her ſo maliciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving the Match of <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> and would no more trouble himſelf with the intrigues of the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> ſince life it ſelf was a burthen to him, did not anſwer theſe advances; nay, he took from her that ſhare ſhe had in the Government of Affairs, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating to the Grand Seignior, that 'twas to bewanting to his own glory, &amp; to violate all the Rules of State Policy, partake his authority with a Woman, who had abuſed it on ſeveral occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> being incenſed at the Grand Viſiers contempt, and well warned of his deſign to get her out of credit, turned all her kindneſs for him into a mortal hatred. She was ſeized with a fit of fury as often as ſhe remembred, that the very Man who was beholding to her for his Life, and which ſhe had raiſed to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minenteſt dignity of the Empire, did now ſlight her, and uſed that credit ſhe had procured him, but to deſtroy her. She looked upon him as a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42523:58"/>
of ingratitude, and found as much pleaſure in contriving a revenge againſt him, than ſhe had done for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly in raiſing him to honours for to content the motions of her love, but the Grand Viſier, who did put to no account all the good Offices he had received from her, ſince that cruel outrage ſhe had made to him, by taking away <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> e'en from his own arms, uſed ſuch precautions near the <hi>Sultan,</hi> that he countermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mothers cunnings, and was ever ſince more abſolute in his Miniſtry, than he had ever been until that time. In the mean while, the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> who was at <hi>Buda</hi> with her Husband, lived a very happy life in appearance; but all the reſpects of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> her Husband, did not hinder her to think ſometimes of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and to feel a great pleaſure in talking of him with <hi>Roxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane;</hi> ſhe did nevertheleſs endeavour to perſwade that Slave, ſhe had wholly forgot him. But <hi>Roxelane,</hi> who knew well her ſentiments was not complaiſant to ſuch a degree, as
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42523:58"/>
to agree with her about it. The Princeſs being aſhamed of the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather knowledge, that Maid had of a Love, which ſhe could not ſtifle, made an effort upon her ſelf, and reſolved to ſet her at liberty, that ſhe might be rid of a Perſon, whoſe preſence did continually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid her with her weakneſs; and that ſhe might the better perſwade the Slave, that ſhe was no more troubled for <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> ſhe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to return to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to ſee the Grand Viſier, to aſſure him, that ſhe lived happy, and that ſhe had ſet her at liberty, meerly to be rid of the ſight of a Woman, that might remember her of her former complaiſance to him. Though that reſolution was moſt contrary to her ſentiments; ſhe thought it however moſt conducive to her glory, to let the Grand Viſier know, that ſhe ſaw his indifferency without grief. This laſt reflection thoroughly determined her, and cauſed her to take meaſures with her Husband, for the Journey of <hi>Roxolane</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42523:59"/>
pretences; aſſoon as ſhe was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at the Port, ſhe failed not to wait upon the Grand Viſier, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived her with a great deal of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. She gave him an account of <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s ſentiments, but with ſo much cunning, that he remained ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, there was leſs indifferency in her anger, than love; from that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he thought himſelf leſs unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, and begun to mind of the means, how to ſee his Princeſs again, he had ſeveral conferences with <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xolana,</hi> who helped him to perceive, that <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s ſo much affecting to be believed happy, ſhewed rather a paſſion not yet well extinguiſhed, than a Soul truly quiet and calm. The Grand Viſier was ſo tranſported with joy at the hearing of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars which ſtill flattered his paſſion, that he forgot nothing to ſhew his gratitude to <hi>Roxelane,</hi> and promiſed her to ſend her back in the Country of her Birth. <hi>Roxelane</hi> not being willing to let ſlip ſo fair an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, intreated him to grant her alſo the liberty of <hi>Donna Emanuela;</hi> but
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42523:59"/>
the Viſier let her underſtand, that it did not lye in his power to do it, becauſe a Slave, who had had the honour to be deſigned to the Grand Seignior's pleaſures, could never up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what colour ſoever, be redeemed or freed; but he aſſured her, that he would never demand of her any thing contrary to her fidelity to <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> though ſhe ſhould be uſed with the ſame reſpect, that was paid to his Wives. <hi>Roxelana</hi> ſeeing 'twas impoſſible for her to obtain <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi>'s freedom, accepted of the Grand Viſier's proffer, and returned in <hi>Italy</hi> overwhelmed with favours, and more happy than ſhe was, before ſhe fell into Slavery.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadors of Count <hi>Teck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> that Famous Chief of the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents in <hi>Hungary,</hi> did at that time renew their intreaties at the Port, to obtain a relief from the <hi>Sultan</hi> againſt the Emperour. The Grand Viſier would fain have made uſe of ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable an occaſion to go, and ſee his Princeſs at the Head of an Army, under the pretence of aſſiſting the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:42523:60"/>
Malecontents; but he had juſt now concluded a Peace with the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and put the Grand Seignior upon the thoughts of other Conqueſts, being both prepoſſeſt, through the intrigues of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that moſt part of the Princes of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> were confederate under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's command, to deſtroy <hi>France,</hi> which could never reſiſt ſo many Puiſſances united againſt it: and not doubting, but in ſuch a happy jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, it would be eaſie for the Grand Seignior's Navy to make themſelves Maſter of Provence, he had already ſent Orders to <hi>Caplan Baſhaw</hi> to put to Sea.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeking a fair Colour to break honeſtly with <hi>France,</hi> It came in his mind to refuſe the honour of the <hi>Sopha</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> Kings Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and engaged the Corſairs of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers</hi> and <hi>Tripoli</hi> to inſult all the Ships of that Nation, they could meet with; aſſuring them of a powerful protection: But ſeeing, the War of the Chriſtian Princes did not facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate any enterpriſe to the Grand
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42523:60"/>
Seignior, and that <hi>France</hi> did ſtill maintain it ſelf, <hi>maugré</hi> that great number of Enemies, he fell into a fit of impatience, and his love made him wiſh, that all that he had been told of the State of Chriſtendom, might prove falſe, to the end, that he might have a pretext to go in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and ſee his Princeſs by the way at <hi>Buda.</hi> Therefore he ſent ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly his Emiſſaries in moſt Courts of the Chriſtian Princeſs, with Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to ſend him a faithful account of the poſture, and condition of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs therein. A little while after he heard, by their reports, which were all found conſentaneous, of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King, the admirable conduct of that Monarch, and of the great diſorder of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. The Grand Viſier acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging thereby, that all he had heard before, was but an effect of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of the Emperor's Emiſſaries, acquainted the <hi>Sultan</hi> withal, and drew him out of that errour, he had himſelf ſo long been in, of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended decay of <hi>France</hi>'s power, but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42523:61"/>
they knew ſoon after with their own experience, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the great was more in condition to give the Law to others, than to receive it of any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The Grand Seignior's <hi>Fleet</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by the ſecret Orders of the Port, the Corſairs of <hi>Algier,</hi> that of <hi>France</hi> blocked up <hi>Caplan Baſhaw</hi> in the Port of <hi>Chio,</hi> and forced him to abandon them to their juſt revenge. The Grand Viſier took no notice of this ſwinging affront, and inſinuated to the Grand Seignior, it was now time to make War in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and make uſe of the ill poſture of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's Affairs, who, aiming at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>France,</hi> had exhauſted his treaſure. So dreadful preparations were made in the whole Empire, that People believed the <hi>Sultan</hi> was going to conquer all Chriſtendom. The <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> was very well pleaſed at this deſign of War, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it might furniſh her with means and occaſions to undo more eaſily the Grand Viſier when abſent from the Port. The Emperour having intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the extraordinary prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42523:61"/>
of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſent Count <hi>Caprara</hi> to <hi>Adrianople,</hi> to treat of Peace, he proffered ſo advantageous terms, that all the <hi>Divan</hi> rejected them with ſcorn, conceiving thereby that the Affairs of the Emperor, were in a moſt deſperate condition.</p>
            <p>All the Troops being aſſembled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Adrianople,</hi> the <hi>Sultan</hi> Muſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and taking a Herontops from his own Turbant, ſet it upon the Grand Viſiers, with all the uſual Ceremonies, to ſhew that he truſted him with all his Authority; 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that <hi>Muſtapha</hi> who had his Friends and Spies in the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> was before his departure warned, the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé</hi> had boaſted, ſhe would undo him in this War, he ſlighted the advice, though he ought to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, ſhe would not fail to turn his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to her advantage, and could, perhaps, get again that great aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſhe had formerly had upon the Grand Seignior<hi>'s</hi> mind; his private friends repreſented unto him, he could not remove himſelf ſo far from the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42523:62"/>
Port, without breaking all the rules of Policy, and endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to accept of Count <hi>Capra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's</hi> propoſals; but he was too much in love, to hearken to their reaſons. Princeſs <hi>Baſchlari</hi>'s Charms did wholly poſſeſs his Heart, and all the powers of his Soul. The meer hope of ſeeing her again, fill'd him with ſo much Joy, that he feared no more to looſe his fortune, conceiving he ſhould not buy ſuch a pleaſure too dear with his own life. Nevertheleſs, becauſe he knew the <hi>Sultaneſſes</hi> Spirit, and that women do ſeldom forgive when they think themſelves to have been ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he reſolved to take from her all means to hurt him, and in order thereunto, to perſwade the <hi>Sultan</hi> to March at the head of his Troops; he urged to him, that the Monarch's preſence gives always much reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to an Army, and that he ought not to doubt but the Chriſtians hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Highneſſes Marching with ſo formidable Troops, would rather crave his mercy with reſpectful ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, than provoke his anger with
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42523:62"/>
an unprofitable reſiſtance. In fine, he did ſo prepoſſeſs him he had no other motive in adviſing him ſo, but a great paſſion for his glory, that the Grand Seignior reſolved to paſs into <hi>Hungary;</hi> and now the Grand Viſier ſeeing himſelf ſecured thereby from all the contrivances of the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> Injoyed before hand, unvaluable plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in thinking that after he had troubled all the World, to put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in meaſures of ſeeing his dear <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> he was gone ſo far that he could ſee no more obſtacles to the performance of his deſign.</p>
            <p>The Grand Seignior parted then from <hi>Adrianople,</hi> at the Head of two Hundred Thouſand Men, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual rain that numerous and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Army was troubled, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt overwhelmed with, the firſt days of its March, ſeemed to many of a very bad omen, the Troops up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their arrival at <hi>Belgrad</hi> were ſo much out of Order, and the Trains ſo haraſſed, that the <hi>Sultan</hi> thought fit to dwell there a long while, that they might have time to be ſet up
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42523:63"/>
again in order. The Grand Viſier longing to ſee <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> wanted not a pretext to go with a ſtrong detach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtraightway to <hi>Buda;</hi> and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt ſhe ſhould be perplexed for the preſence of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, he ſent him Orders to go and joyn Count <hi>Teckley,</hi> and both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to relieve <hi>Newheuſel,</hi> which was threatned with a Siege by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. The Princeſs who had a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand reaſons to be fully ſatisfied with her Husband, hearing of <hi>Muſtapha</hi>'s coming to <hi>Buda,</hi> fancied at firſt ſhe could ſee him without trouble; ſhe did nevertheleſs miſtruſt her own heart, and to avoid any return of her former tenderneſs for a Man whom ſhe had judged worthy of her eſteem, ſhe recalled in her mind, with how much ingratitude this Grand Viſier had ſacrificed her to his ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious projects, and at the ſame time, reflected upon thoſe great obligations her Husband had laid upon her, and with how much reſpect and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance he had uſed her ever ſince their Marriage. Theſe tumultuous
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:42523:63"/>
thoughts inſpired her with ſo much pride, that far from being afraid of the Viſier's arrival, ſhe longed to ſee him, that ſhe might have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to ſhew him a great indifferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; he arrived at laſt, and demanded to wait upon the Princeſs from the Grand Seignior. She received him in State, and in an attire, which did ſo much ſet off her natural beauty, that the Grand Viſier was extremely moved at it, he complemented her firſt in the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s name, and would next perſwade her, that he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver performed his Highneſſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands with ſo much contentment, as now. The Princeſs anſwered him haughtily, and with a ſet malice aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him, that the beſt token the <hi>Sultan</hi> her Brother could give her of his love, was quickly to ſend her Husband home. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed at a repartee ſo contrary to his Love, pretended, he had orders to acquaint her with the operations of the Campaign, and the Princeſſes Women and Eunuchs being retired at a diſtance, he complained of her
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42523:64"/>
coldneſs, and uſed the tendereſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to ſatisfie her of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of his paſſion. The Princeſs let him know, ſhe had followed his Example, but however would not take it ill from him, ſince ſhe had been ſo fortunate, as to fall into the hands of a Husband, who was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, the moſt honeſt Man in the Empire. The Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier deeply penetrated with grief, cryed out againſt the injuſtice ſhe was doing to him, by believing him liable to change, he afterwards diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to her all thoſe tricks where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mother had broken their Match, and told her at laſt, that not being able to live any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, without the happineſs of ſeeing her, he had moved the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior to renew the War in <hi>Hungary,</hi> that he might have occaſion to come and dye at her Feet, if he were ſo unhappy as to be indifferent to her. The Princeſs, who had till now been ignorant of theſe ſo material circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances for the juſtification of her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, was ſo much moved by them,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:42523:64"/>
and that pride, which is intailed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family, was ſo much ſatisfied to ſee, that a paſſion ſhe was the cauſe of, had put all <hi>Europe</hi> in Arms, that in ſpight of all her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards her Husband, her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs carried it over all the other motions of her heart. She ſpoke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kindly to <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> and after having bitterly inveighed againſt the <hi>Sultaneſs Validé,</hi> ſhe could not forbear confeſſing ſhe was for the future, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of a very unhappy life, well foreſeeing ſhe ſhould feel an equal trouble to reſiſt her paſſion on one ſide; and to weaken that great eſteem ſhe had already for her Husband on the other, a flood, of tears poured down from her eyes at theſe words; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſired <hi>Muſtapha</hi> to retire, ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led back her Women, and told them, ſhe had not been able to keep in her tears, conceiving through the Grand Viſiers diſcourſe, this would be a Bloody War, and her Husband ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to great dangers therein. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>Muſtapha</hi> were extremely glad for his being at laſt juſtified in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42523:65"/>
the Princeſſes mind, and had reaſon to be contented with thoſe ſigns ſhe had given him, of what paſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her heart in his favour; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he looked upon the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> as a rival, who had robbed him of his treaſure; he was ſeized with ſo ſtrong a jealouſie, that he reſolved to remove him ſpeedily from the Princeſs; he revolved a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times in his mind all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of his converſation with her, and knowing ſhe was above all tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with a great ſhew of merit and vertue, he thought, that if he could command the Army in his own Perſon, it would be eaſie to dazle her with ſome ſhining action. Therefore he made ſpeed to rejoyn the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, whom he endeavoured to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade 'twas fit he ſhould ſtay at <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grad,</hi> and leave to him all the care of this War. The <hi>Sultan</hi> at firſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it; but as able Miniſters do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want means and reaſons to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to their ends, the Grand Viſier repreſented to his Highneſs, that if he ſhould advance farther in the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:42523:65"/>
Chriſtian Territories, his being ſo far removed from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> might give way to ſome Rebellion; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if he would reſide at <hi>Belgrad,</hi> no inſurrection was to be feared at home, and he ſhould be near enough the Army to reap all the Glory of the Conqueſts to be made. The <hi>Sultan</hi> being overpowered with theſe reaſons followed the Counſel of <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> who being deſirous to do any thing, that might ſhine to <hi>Baſch lari</hi>'s Eyes, he reſolved to begin the <hi>Campaign</hi> with the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and ſent Orders to the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> the Princeſſes Husband to block up the place, he Marched afterwards, at the Head of an Hundred and Threeſcore Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men to beſiege it actually; his Troops to terrifie the Chriſtians, plundered and killed all that they met with in their March. Aſſoon as the Siege was formed, the Grand Viſier Summoned Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> Governour of the place to ſurrender it, aſſuring him of the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior's friendſhip, if he would deſerve it by a ſpeedy Submiſſion to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42523:66"/>
but threatning him at the ſame time, that in caſe he would be ſo raſh as to reſiſt, and force him to expoſe and ſhed the Blood of the <hi>Muſſulmans,</hi> he ſhould put all to the edge of the Sword, without ſparing either Age or Sex; nay, that he would excogitate a new torment for him in particular. Count <hi>Staremberg</hi> ſlighted this inſolent <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Rodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montade, and prepared to diſcharge his truſt like a Gallant Man, by a ſtout and vigorous defence; he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Suburbs of <hi>Vienna</hi> to be Burnt, and ſo much encouraged both with deeds and words, the Soldiers and Citizens of the place, that they made a moſt ſolemn vow to defend it even to the laſt drop of their blood. The <hi>Turks</hi> attacked at firſt with much valour, but were beaten back, and loſt a vaſt number of Men. The Grand Viſier, whom the conduct of this Siege did not trouble ſo much as his love, had conceived an unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able hatred for the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> he thought he had done but little to remove him from the Princeſs <hi>Baſch-lari;</hi>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:42523:66"/>
his Jealouſie demanded a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sacrifice, and inſpired him with a dark deſign to ſeek his Death, fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying this War gave him a fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to rid himſelf handſomly, and without fear of the leaſt ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, of ſo potent and troubleſom a rival. So he called one day the Council of War, and after having complained of the length of the Siege, he moved for a general aſſault, which he got reſolved upon againſt the opinion of his moſt experienced Officers. The <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> was commanded to head the detachment, though he was one of them, who had voted againſt this raſh enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. Nevertheleſs, he diſcharged his duty with much valour; but the Chriſtians being encouraged with their former happy ſucceſſes, ſlew many Thouſand of <hi>Turks,</hi> and forced the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> to a retreat, to ſave the ſmall remnant of his Troops; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Grand Viſier blamed his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and charged upon him this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſucceſs, which did not vex him ſo much, becauſe of the great
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42523:67"/>
number of Soldiers killed, as becauſe the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> had eſcaped the danger. In the mean while, a report was ſpread of the great King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s Marching toward the relief of <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> The <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> who was a great Commander, moved in the Council that a ſtrong body of Troops ſhould be ſent forthwith, to hinder the junction of the King's Army with the Emperor's, and made it appear, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> could not approach the place without Marching through ſeveral narrow paſſages, which few Armed Men were able to keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Power of an Army, but the Grand Viſier, would not hearken to this prudent Counſel, and proudly anſwered, they muſt be let come, that the <hi>Sultan</hi> might be revenged upon them, for the great loſſes he had ſuffered during this Siege. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine, upon the Twelfth of <hi>September</hi> 1683. the Chriſtian Army was ſeen upon the Hills of <hi>Vienna.</hi> The Grand Viſier, who relyed upon the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his Men, thought, he could well Fight the Chriſtians, and carry
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42523:67"/>
the Siege on both together, left a ſtrong body of Janiſſaries in the Trenches, and commanded another detachment to ſtrengthen them, and hinder the Sallies of the beſieged. Afterwards he Marched with the main Body, to fight the Chriſtians, and conceiving that notwithſtanding the huge inequality of both Armies, the firſt ſhok was like to be very cruel, he thought it might prove favourable to his jealouſie, by occaſioning the death of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda.</hi> Therefore he commanded him to go and meet the Chriſtians, forbidding him to retire, what effort ſoever they could make againſt him, and aſſuring him to be backed with the whole Army; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he was ſo confident of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, that he would have all his Wives mounted on Horſe-back, and upon Camels to behold from a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Hill, the defeat of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; nay, they did already rejoyce before hand, for that imaginary Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, and attributed great praiſes to the Grand Viſier. The only <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:42523:68"/>
Emanuela,</hi> who heard talk of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but of projects fatal to Chriſtendom, was continually weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; one of them, that was moſt of all in the Grand Viſier's favour, and had always feared leſt this Chriſtian Slave's Beauty, might ingage her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, moved to her to paſs into the Camp of the <hi>Polanders,</hi> ſince ſhe found herſelf ſo unhappy amongſt the <hi>Muſſulmans. Donna Emanuela</hi> let her underſtand, that her eſcape was not altogether impoſſible, if ſhe would countenance it. The Viſier's Wife being very deſirous to be rid of a Perſon, that could contend with her for Beauty; promiſed her, ſhe would contribute to it with her utmoſt Power, and truſted with her deſign two other Women, who had the ſame intereſt in <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi>'s eſcape. In the mean time, the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> was beaten back, and his Troops having had no ſuccour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired in ſuch a diſorder, that they broke a great part of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The Chriſtians purſued them very cloſe, and the <hi>Turks</hi> having no
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42523:68"/>
time to rally, loſt a great number of Men. The fright was general, and many a ſquadron retired without fighting, or daring ſo much as to approach the Chriſtians. The Grand Viſier had much ado to keep in the Soldiers that fled on all ſides; he did nevertheleſs, in ſuch a hurly-burly cover with much are the diſorder of his Troops, and without ſeeming to be forced to decamp, he made them retire with ſpeed; nay, he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him the Janiſſaries, who were in the Trenches, leſt he ſhould be diſcovered in his retreat; but <hi>Donna Emanuela,</hi> who had contrived with the Grand Viſier's Wives to make her eſcape, aſſoon as Night would help it, made uſe of the <hi>Turks</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation, and paſſed with little or to pain into the Chriſtian Army. She was brought before the King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and acquainted his Majeſty with the Flight of the <hi>Turks,</hi> who Fled with ſo much precipitation, that they had abandoned their Tents, and all their baggage. The King won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the great courage of that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42523:69"/>
Heroine, and becauſe he did not well underſtand <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> he ſent for ſome Cavalier of that Nation in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror's Army. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> ſent a Man of quality, who ſerved under him as adjutant General. The King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who had a mind to know the condition of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army, commanded him to ask that Maid ſeveral queſtions, but aſſoon as <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi> had caſt her eyes upon him, ſhe knew him to be her dear <hi>Don Gaspard,</hi> and ſwooned away at the King's Feet. It was not long e're ſhe recovered of her ſwoon, through the cares of <hi>Don Gaſpard,</hi> who was ready to dye with joy, to ſee ſo unexpectedly that charming Maid; as the King wondered at ſuch an extraordinary adventure, <hi>Don Gaſpard</hi> acquainted him with <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi>'s quality, and how far they were bound one to another. The King's preſence could not hinder many tender expreſſions to paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them both at ſo ſweet and charming a remembrance. <hi>Donna E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuela</hi> put an end to them, being
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:42523:69"/>
deſired to relate the particulars of the <hi>Turks</hi> diſorder, and the fright of their Camp, when ſhe made her eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape. The King made ſo good uſe of her advice, that without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, he purſued the Enemy, cut in pieces the Janiſſaries, who guarded the Trenches, and made himſelf Maſter of all the baggage and Tents of that numerous Army, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both the Grand Viſier's pavillion, and all the others ſtill ſet up, he charged afterwards their rear, and ſhould have certainly defeated the whole Army, had he had Troops e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ready to ſtop the paſſages to the Grand Viſier. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> who had flattered himſelf, that he could make retreat without being purſued by the Chriſtians, hearing of <hi>Donna Emanuela</hi>'s eſcape, and of all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that attended it, doubted not but ſhe would inform the King of <hi>Poland</hi> of the diſmal condition, he was brought unto, for which he ſell ſo grievous angry with all thoſe, that had favoured or countenanced her Flight, that he cauſed preſently
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:42523:70"/>
four of his Wives, and two Eunuchs to be Beheaded. In the mean time, though the loſs of ſo many fine Troops did much trouble him, yet becauſe he referred all things to his love, his heart was far leſs vexed at the raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Siege, than at the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi>'s ſtill living <hi>maugré</hi> all the tricks he had made uſe of, to deſtroy him; and conceiving, this <hi>Baſhaw</hi> might upbraid him before the <hi>Sultan</hi> with the ſo many groſs faults he had committed in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Siege, he reſolved to prepoſſeſs his Maſter's mind, and to charge before hand upon the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> all the misfortunes which had befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len the Army; but when he reflected, that the Grand Seignior might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps forgive him for his Wife's ſake, and that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> ſhould find how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a great comfort within the Arms of the Princeſs <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> this thought tormented him to ſuch a degree, that without any farther examination, he gave himſelf over to the impetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his vengeance, and cauſed this great but unfortunate <hi>Baſhaw</hi> to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42523:70"/>
be Strangled; and to avoid the ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion that any private grudge might have influenced in this ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſerved ſo two other <hi>Baſhaws</hi> whom he accuſed of ill conduct, and cowardiſe in the diſcharge of their duty. Every one was amazed at ſo bold an action, but the Viſier did not matter much the murmurs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of the People, he was only troubled about <hi>Baſch lari,</hi> how ſhe ſhould receive this news. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, knowing that moſt Women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the loſs of their Husbands, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for decency's ſake, and do eaſily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the dead in favour of the living, he hoped that the remedy of time, and his cares ſhould diminiſh her an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Therefore being pritty well freed from fear on that ſide, he bent all his wits to find a way, how to juſtifie himſelf before the Grand Seignior; he ſent a truſty friend of his to <hi>Belgrad,</hi> and let the <hi>Sultan</hi> underſtand, that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> looking upon his Highneſſes Conqueſts with a jealous eye, and foreſeeing <hi>Buda</hi> ſhould no more be a
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42523:71"/>
Frontier after the taking of <hi>Vienna,</hi> had croſſed with all manner of obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles the ſucceſs of that enterpriſe; that he had been contented at firſt to upbraid him with it, in hope that a man, who had the honour to be ſo near related to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, would ſoon acknowledge his fault, and endeavour to make amends for it; but that the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> abuſing his moderation, had perſiſted in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſentiments, and that after he had been ſuch a coward, as to fly before a handful of Chriſtians, he had broken the ranks of the <hi>Muſſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and put the whole Army into confuſion; that two <hi>Baſhaws</hi> having been frighted like Children, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed the diſorder, of which the Chriſtians had made ſo good uſe, that if he had not uſed all neceſſary precautions to keep in the flying Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and to make an orderly and honourable retreat, all his Highneſſes Army, had run the danger to be cut in pieces; that afterwards having had intelligence, that thoſe <hi>Baſhaws</hi> being aſhamed of their cowardiſe, were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:42523:71"/>
making ſecret Cabals, that might be of a dangerous conſequence, he had judged it neceſſary to puniſh the criminals without any delay, that he might by their death ſtop the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in its cradle; nay he aſſured him, that having no more Traitors nor Cowards in his Army, he ſhould advantageouſly repair in the next Campaign, the loſſes he had made by the ill conduct of thoſe unworthy Officers. The Grand Seignior being perſwaded by the reaſons, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of the zeal of his Viſier, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of all he had done, and as a witneſs of his ſatisfaction, he ſent him a new Standard with Seven Horſe tales, aſſuring him he would for ever honour him with his favour, and provide him abundantly with all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, that he might be enabled to revenge upon the Chriſtians, the great affront he had received at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Princeſs heard very confuſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of her Husband's Death, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, he had been ſlain in the War, her grief hindered her to hearken to
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42523:72"/>
the other circumſtances of his death, which none was very forward to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her with. She pay'd a great tribute of Tears to his Memory, but was ſoon comforted with the thought that the Grand Viſier loved her ſtill, he arrived at <hi>Buda</hi> about that time, to receive there the great Standard the Grand Seignior had ſent to him, together with all the Teſtimonies of his eſteem, he might wiſh for. So being aſſured again of his Maſters favour, he thought of nothing but to clear himſelf before the Princeſs, he could not but know how great was her eſteem for her Husband, and he doubted a while whither he ſhould ſee her, or no, but the new tokens he had juſt now received of the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>'s kindneſs, made him ſo proud, or rather his love made him ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient, that he reſolved to demand an audience of <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> pretending he had an Order from the Grand Seignior to communicate to her. The Princeſs received him with a great ſhew of ſadneſs, and deſired him to
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42523:72"/>
give her time to wipe off her Tears. The Grand Viſier, who expected a greater tranſport, becauſe he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhe knew already, what kind of Death had robbed her of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, begun his own apology; and told her, he had paſſed by the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi>'s faults, as long as he could; but that having occaſioned the loſs of the beſt part of the Army, he durſt not put off his puniſhment any longer, for fear of expoſing his own Head to the Grand Seignior's wrath. <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> was ready to dye with grief at this diſcourſe, which let her know, that her Husband was dead both by the Hangman's hand, and by the order of her Lover. Theſe cruel circumſtances vexed her ſo much the more, becauſe ſhe could not but be conſcious of her having had a great ſhare in his crime, her love did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs plead for the Viſier, but ſhe was ſeized with ſuch an horrour for his cruelties, that <hi>maugré</hi> all the ſecret motions of her heart, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled him grievouſly, and threatned him to Strangle him with her own
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:42523:73"/>
hands, except he would preſently be gone; when he was retired, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned her tranſport, and though ſhe was ſatisfied of the juſtice of her grief, yet ſhe perceived, her anger had made her ſpeak againſt her true ſentiments; but revolving in her mind a minute after, that neither the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he owed to her, nor the fear of diſpleaſing her, had been able to take him from the black deſign of Strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her Husband, ſhe thought her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf highly injured by ſo criminal a boldneſs, and that both glory and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty obliged her to be revenged of <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha</hi>'s cruelty. Theſe laſt ſentiments prevailing upon her, ſhe was aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of her weakneſs; and believing, ſhe had overcome the ſecret revolt of her heart in the Grand Viſier's favour, ſhe departed from <hi>Buda</hi> for <hi>Belgrad,</hi> with a firm reſolution to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the Grand Seignior againſt <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha,</hi> about the unjuſt Death of her Husband. In the mean time, the Grand Viſier, who reſented to the quick the Princeſſes anger, did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour with gifts to draw in her
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:42523:73"/>
Women and Eunuchs to his intereſt, perſwading himſelf, that time and love would do the reſt. Neither did he neglect to write to the Grand Seignior, and prepoſſeſs him upon <hi>Baſch-lari</hi>'s diſcontent, he let him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, amongſt other things, he could hardly imagine, that a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Blood, could be ſorry for the Death of a Husband, who had no courage; his Letter had more effect than he expected. The <hi>Sultan</hi> ſeeking to juſtifie his Viſier by all means, that might ſhine to the Eyes of the People, ſend Orders to the Princeſs not to come to <hi>Belgrad,</hi> and letting her know, he would ſee nothing, that might remember him of a Man, who had made himſelf unworthy of the honour of his alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, he ſent her back to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> attended by a Miniſter of the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> who declared to her that the Grand Seignior being willing, to condemn the Memory of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda</hi> to an eternal oblivion, and to blot out the remembrance of his alliance, with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42523:74"/>
had made choice of <hi>Baſhaw Ibrahim</hi> to be his Brother in Law; he told her farther, the <hi>Sultan</hi> would very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly own her to be his Siſter, and ſee her with pleaſure, aſſoon as he could look upon her, as the Wife of a Man whom he loved, not as the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a Traytor. <hi>Baſch-lari</hi> was at firſt ſurpriſed at this harangue; but when ſhe had made reflection, that 'twas not lawful for her to oppoſe the Grand Seignior's Command, and that, by this Match ſhe could both revenge the Death of her late Husband, and free herſelf from the cruel neceſſity, ſhe was in, to ſpeak againſt her Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhe conſented with leſs repugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to Marry <hi>Baſham Ibrahim,</hi> who was a Young Man endowed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent parts. A little while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Grand Seignior arrived at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where he received his Siſter with all the reſpect ſhe might wiſh for; and now conceiving it would be a pleaſant piece of news to the Grand Viſier; which he had leſt at <hi>Belgrad,</hi> he acquainted him with that Marriage, to ſhew him that he ſought
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:42523:74"/>
to deſtroy the Memory of the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Buda,</hi> by all means that lyed in his Power. The Grand Viſier, who had flattered himſelf, that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſhould be appeaſed by length of time, was mighty troubled at the news of her being Married, and when he knew, that <hi>Baſhaw Ibrahim</hi> had reaped the fruit of all the pains he had taken, to undo that of <hi>Buda;</hi> he fell into ſo deep a Melancholly, that he troubled himſelf no more, either to keep his credit, or maintain his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; he had advice, the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was about making new cabals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and that <hi>Gran</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the Chriſtians, but he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to relieve that place, and ſcorned to go and juſtifie himſelf to the Grand Seignior, chooſing rather to periſh, than to be a witneſs of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw Ibrahim</hi>'s happineſs. The Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Port, being tired with the Tyranny of the Viſier, who had loſt by his fault the beſt Troops of the Empire, had vainly attempted to deſtroy him in the <hi>Sultan</hi>'s mind, but after the taking of <hi>Gran</hi> by the Duke
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42523:75"/>
of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> the <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> did ſerve her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo well of this favourable jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that the Grand Seignior being amazed at the dayly reports of the ill poſture of his Affairs, begun to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Sentiments for the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier. Now, the Janiſſaries who could not find in their hearts, to forgive him the foul trick he had plaid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, in abandoning their Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rads to the fury of the Chriſtians, at the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and being coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by the ſecret contrivances of the <hi>Sultaneſs,</hi> they did tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly repair before the <hi>Serraglio,</hi> and demanded the Head of that Miniſter; as the preſent condition of Affairs rendered ſuch ſeditions very danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the <hi>Sultan</hi> ſpoke to them with much courage and firmneſs, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome Money to be diſtributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, he diſmiſſed them with hope, that he would mind how to ſee them ſatisfied. The <hi>Sultaneſs</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the Grand Viſier's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, renewed their intereſt againſt him, and endeavoured to perſwade his Highneſs, that the Empire was
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:42523:75"/>
threatned with a general inſurrection, except he would ſacrifice his Viſier to the publick hatred; at laſt, the Grand Seignior conſented, the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould be referred to the <hi>Mufti</hi>'s judgment, his caſe was brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der borrowed names, before him, who after a long debate thereof with the ableſt Divines of the Empire, voted at laſt, and wrote with his own hand, that he who had committed thoſe faults, which he had juſt now exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was worthy of Death. The Grand Seignior did nevertheleſs keep this reſolve ſecret a great while, but being preſſed by his Mother, he made choice of two <hi>Agas</hi> of the Janiſſaries, which he knew to be Wiſemen, and giving them in charge to behave themſelves with an extraordinary prudence, he gave them a Hatcherif, and commanded them to go ſecretly to <hi>Belgrad,</hi> and Strangle the Grand Viſier. The two <hi>Agas</hi> being arrived at <hi>Belgrad,</hi> let <hi>Muſtapha</hi> underſtand, they were ſent by the Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to take juſt meaſures with him, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the things he might want for,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42523:76"/>
to be ready againſt the next Spring to take the Field, and repair by ſome great exploit the miſcarriage of the laſt Campaign. The Viſier who was not ignorant of the Plot, that was a hatching againſt him at the Port, had ſome ſuſpicion, that their errand was only to demand his Head, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed a while to give them audience. The two Wiſe <hi>Agas</hi> ſhewed no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience at all to ſee him, on the contrary they ſent him word, that they came meerly to wait for his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and would ſtay as long as he pleaſed. This prudent carriage de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Viſier; he aſſembled the <hi>Divan,</hi> and received the two <hi>Agas,</hi> one of them ſerved him with the <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi>'s Hatcherif, which was packed up in a ſmall Bag of Velvet; at the ſame time the other <hi>Agas</hi> untied his Girdle, made up with ſeveral little ſilk twiſts, and threw it upon the Grand Viſier's neck, who was reading the firſt lines of the Warrant, he ſeemed to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, named the Princeſs without explaining himſelf farther, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving upon the face of the Officers,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42523:76"/>
that ſate about him, no motion, which might put him in hopes of a revolt in his favour, he deſired the <hi>Agas</hi> to grant him time for a ſhort Prayer, and then was Strangled; his Head was carried with ſpeed to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> where it made a very pleaſant Spectacle to the People, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Janiſſaries. The only <hi>Baſch-lari,</hi> who loved him ſtill, <hi>maugré</hi> all the reaſons ſhe had to complain of him, paid Tears to his Memory, and not being able to endure, that the Head of a Man, whom ſhe had ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with her eſteem, ſhould be expoſed to the ſcoffs of the rabble, cauſed it to be ſecretly taken away, and decently Buried.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42523:77"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
